<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvorkeman, that needeth not to be ashamed: or The faithfull steward of Gods house A sermon describing the duety of a godly minister, both in his doctrine and in his life. By Charles Richardson, preacher at S. Katharines, neere the Tower of London.</title>
            <author>Richardson, Charles, fl. 1612-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10740</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21019</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115966</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851183</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851183</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16447</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10740)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16447)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1360:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvorkeman, that needeth not to be ashamed: or The faithfull steward of Gods house A sermon describing the duety of a godly minister, both in his doctrine and in his life. By Charles Richardson, preacher at S. Katharines, neere the Tower of London.</title>
                  <author>Richardson, Charles, fl. 1612-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 71, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Stansby, for William Barret, and are to be sold at his shop in Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the three Pigeons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-K⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The faithfull steward of Gods house.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16447:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16447:1"/>
            <p>A WORKEMAN, <hi>That</hi> NEEDETH NOT TO BE ASHAMED: <hi>OR The faithfull Steward of Gods houſe.</hi> A Sermon deſcribing the duety of a godly MINISTER, both in his DOCTRINE and in his LIFE.</p>
            <p>By CHARLES RICHARDSON, Preacher at S. KATHARINES, neere the Tower of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LVKE 12.42.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Who is a faithfull and wiſe Steward, whom his Lord ſhall make ruler ouer his houſhold, to giue them their portion of meate in due ſeaſon?</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. Stansby,</hi> for <hi>William Barret,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Paules</hi> Church-yard, at the ſigne of the three Pigeons. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16447:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16447:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO MY REVEREND GOOD FRIEND M<hi rend="sup">R</hi>. D. SPARKE, MINISTER OF GODS WORD AT BLETCHLEY IN BVCKINGHAMSHIRE, Grace and Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, I preſent vnto you here a Sermon, pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by mee, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the duety of a Godly Miniſter. I confeſſe, it may be thought great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, that I, who am the leaſt of many thouſands of my brethren, ſhould take vpon me
<pb facs="tcp:16447:3"/>to teach others,<note n="*" place="margin">Magis mihi diſcendum quam docen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,
<hi>Macrob. Saturn. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> who ſtand more need to learne my ſelfe. But I may truly ſay, as<note n="a" place="margin">Sui magis admonendi, quam aliorum docendi gratia,
<hi>lib.</hi> 16. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>A. Gellius</hi> ſaid of a certaine booke of
<hi>Laelius,</hi> That I writ it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for mine owne admonition, then for the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of others. Whatſoeuer it is, I am bold to publiſh it to the view of the world in your name, both in regard of that deſire I haue to teſtifie my thankefulneſſe vnto you, for the great and vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued kindneſſe, I haue many waies found at your hands, eſpecially for that (as I doe willingly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge) you were the firſt that perſwaded and encouraged me to enter into the Miniſtery, and the firſt place which I had in the Church, I had of your free gift: and alſo in reſpect of that reuerence, which I beare vnto your graue and venerable old Age:<note n="b" place="margin">Venerabilis non annorum ſed virtutum numero, <hi>Bern. de amore Dei, part.</hi>
2.</note> Venerable, I ſay, not ſo much in number of yeeres (though they bee very many) as in aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of vertue. It is not with you, as it is with too many, who being decrepit with age, and ready to be laid on the Beere,<note n="c" place="margin">Senec. de breuit. vitae.</note> haue no other argument to proue that they haue liued long, but their gray haires and their wrinckles. But you haue verified that ſpeech of <hi>SALOMON, Age is a crowne of glory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 16.31.</note> when it is found in the way of righteouſneſſe. <hi>The paines that you haue taken
<pb facs="tcp:16447:3"/>in the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.2.</note> in preaching the word <hi>in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon</hi> (as the Apoſtle commandeth) will no doubt make you famous to poſterity: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſidering, that euen now when your ſtrength is ſpent, and your body worne, ſo as you might iuſtly with<note n="*" place="margin">—Veianius armis Herculis ad poſtem fixis latet abditus agro, <hi>Horat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Veianius,</hi> long agoe haue han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vp your armour, and betaken your ſelfe to reſt, yet ſtill you continue your wonted labour, as though you deſired to end your life &amp; your preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both at once. And when you ſhall be gathered hence as a ricke of Corne, you ſhall ſuruiue in thoſe three worthy Sonnes of yours,<note place="margin">M. Thomas Sparke of New Colledge in Oxford. M. Andrew Sparke of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-houſe in Cambridge. M. William Sparke of Magdalen Colledge in Oxford.</note> whom you haue beene carefull to traine vp in the Schooles of the Prophets; two of them being already profitable Miniſters in the Church; and the third, as he hath attayned to a great meaſure of learning: ſo, I doubt not, but he will imploy it to the edification of the body of Christ. But I am not willing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne you with any further mention of theſe things. I beſeech you to accept of theſe weake me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, with the ſame minde and affection, wherewith I offer them. And howſoeuer, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,<note place="margin">Cypr. in Symbolum Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolorum.</note> they be not worthy the exerciſe of great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines: yet if hereby I may excite ſome yong be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners, to the more conſcionable diſcharge of their
<pb facs="tcp:16447:4"/>dueties, I ſhall thinke my labour well beſtowed. I pray God ſtill to bleſſe your godly labours, that when you ſhall haue finiſhed your courſe, you may receiue that Crowne of righteouſneſſe, which is laid vp for you in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your W. in all Chriſtian affection, CHARLES RICHARDSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page, 15. lin. 8. for <hi>happines</hi> reade <hi>hearers.</hi> p. 21. l. 27. for <hi>and,</hi> r. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 23. l. 32. after <hi>find,</hi> r. <hi>them.</hi> p. 26. l. 14. for
<hi>Trade,</hi> r. <hi>flaile.</hi> p. 42. l. 5. for <hi>with.</hi> r. <hi>to.</hi> p. 45. l. 23. put out theſe words. <hi>and the worke is an eſtabliſhment to the life.</hi> p. 46. l. 27. after <hi>filthineſſe,</hi> r. <hi>might.</hi> p 47. l. 31. for <hi>heal,</hi> r.
<hi>heart.</hi> p. 55. l. 34. for <hi>they,</hi> r. <hi>he.</hi> p. 67. l. 27. for
<hi>filleth,</hi> r. <hi>fitteth.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16447:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON, DESCRIBING THE DVTY OF A GODLY MINISTER.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. TIM. 2.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Study to ſhew thy ſelfe approued vnto God, a Worke-man that needeth not to be aſhamed, diuiding the Word of truth aright.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Timotheus,</hi> to whom both theſe Epiſtles are written, hauing beene brought vp in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from his cradle;<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi>
3.15.</note> and hauing alwaies been faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the profeſſion of Chriſtian Religion, was therefore in very great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation with the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Paul;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16.3.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.4. <hi>&amp; Rom.</hi> 16.21.</note> and was either one of his Companions in his peregrinations; or elſe when the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> himſelfe was kept in priſon, he imployed him as a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> and ſent him to confirme the Churches which he had planted. Thus was he ſent to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.2.</note>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:16447:5"/>
               <hi>To put them in remembrance</hi> of that which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> had taught. Thus was he alſo ſent to the <hi>Theſſalonians, To eſtabliſh them, and to comfort them touching their faith.</hi> For this cauſe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.
<hi>&amp;</hi> 16.10. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.2. Act. 16.9.10.1.
<hi>Tim.</hi> 1.3.</note> whereſoeuer the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> maketh mention of him, he doth alwayes giue him very great commendation. Now, when the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> was himſelfe to depart into <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia,</hi> where the Lord had called him by a viſion <hi>to preach the Goſpell;</hi> he left <hi>Timotheus</hi> at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> to reſiſt the falſe Teachers, which were crept into the Church, and began to corrupt ſound doctrine, thereby to draw men from the ſinceritie of faith. And becauſe there was not yet a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient number of
<hi>Miniſters</hi> in the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> to preach the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> therefore the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> giueth him autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to ordayne as many as ſhould be needfull. And for his better direction in ſo waighty a buſineſſe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi>
3.15.</note> hee writeth the former Epiſtle vnto him, teaching him, what hee is chiefly to reſpect in the impoſition of hands, and ſhewing, who are to be admitted vnto that great and high calling, and who are to be reiected.</p>
            <p>And becauſe <hi>Timotheus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.4.</note> as a louing
<hi>Schollar,</hi> was much grieued, and ſhed many teares, at the departure of ſo kind a Maſter,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.14.</note> therefore to comfort him, the
<hi>Apoſtle</hi> promiſed in the former <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> if it were poſſible, to come vnto him againe very ſhortly. But being in the meane while carried as a priſoner to
<hi>Rome,</hi> and hauing now no hope euer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe to <hi>Epheſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim</hi> 4.6.</note> but rather looking euery day for preſent death: hee writeth this ſecond <hi>Epiſtle</hi> vnto <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus,</hi> both to confirme and arme him againſt the feare of perſecution, which in regard of his youth might trouble and diſmay him: and alſo, to direct him further, how to behaue himſelfe in the gouernement of Gods Church.</p>
            <p>But not to ſpend time in vn-folding the whole <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> but to come neere the wordes that are to bee handled; in this ſecond Chapter, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> firſt of all exhorteth
<hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motheus</hi> vnto cheerefulneſſe, and diligence in preaching of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and to appoint meet and ſufficient <hi>Miniſters,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16447:5"/>for the propagating of ſound doctrine vnto poſteritie; which exhortation, with the reaſons of it, is continued vnto the 9. verſe. Secondly, hee comforteth him by many arguments, both againſt that offence he might take at his bonds and impriſonment, and alſo againſt the feare of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, which might befall himſelfe likewiſe: and that vnto the
14. verſe. Thirdly, becauſe euen then the Church began to be troubled with contentions, diſputations, and ſtrife about words, in the 14. verſe he exhorteth him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine them to the vttermoſt of his power. And firſt, the more to terrifie thoſe that delighted in ſuch peeuiſh oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, he bids him vſe great vehemency of ſpeech in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing them, euen to
<hi>proteſt vnto them before the Lord;</hi> thereby inſinuating, how dangerous a thing this litigious and wrangling knowledge is. Then he ſetteth downe two arguments to diſſwade from them, taken from the vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable effects of them. Firſt, that they are <hi>to no profit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Altercando ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas amittitur, <hi>Caluin. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi>
               </note> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Teachers themſelues, who thereby come to loſe the truth: nor yet to their Hearers, who by ſuch courſes are not at all built vp in Faith and Charitie, which is the true vſe of Chriſtian doctrine.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.</note> Secondly, that ſuch contentions are ſo farre from profiting, as that rather they tend to the <hi>peruerting of the hearers:</hi> turning them away from true Faith, and ſo conſequently, from euerlaſting ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <p>Now, becauſe as <hi>Caluin</hi> obſerueth, all this ſtirre and ſtrife in doctrine ariſeth from this Fountayne, that men of good, but vnſanctified wits, deſire in a vaine oſtentation to vaunt and ſet forth themſelues and their gifts before men: therefore, the
<hi>Apoſtle</hi> in this verſe, preſcribeth a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent remedie for that diſeaſe, exhorting <hi>Timotheus,</hi> and all other in his place, to caſt their eyes vpon God, making it their chiefe ſtudie to approue themſelues to him, in the faithfull execution of their miniſterie, and in the ſincere performance of thoſe dueties which God requireth of them. As if he ſhould ſay, Let others that delight in it,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16447:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſeeke to win the applauſe of men: but doe thou ſtudie to approue thy ſelfe and thy miniſterie vnto God. And thus doe theſe wordes depend on that which went before. In the handling whereof, for our more orderly proceeding, let vs conſider theſe two things: firſt, the duetie where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> exhorteth <hi>Timotheus:</hi> and ſecondly, the meanes preſcribed for the better performance thereof. The duetie is this, that he
<hi>ſtudie to approue him ſelfe to God.</hi> The meanes whereby this may be effected, are two: firſt, if <hi>he be a worke-man,</hi> and ſuch a one <hi>as needeth not to be aſhamed.</hi> Secondly, if he <hi>diuide the Word of truth aright.</hi> And thus much for the opening and reſoluing of the wordes. Let vs now proceede to the doctrines and inſtructions, that ariſe from them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Studie to ſhew thy ſelfe approued to God.</hi>)<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> à <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio.</hi>
               </note> The word that is rendred
<hi>ſtudie,</hi> is of great force in the <hi>originall,</hi> and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth to endeuour to the vttermoſt of ones power, to vſe al diligence, and euen to inforce a mans ſelfe to doe a thing, and ſo it is vſed and tranſlated,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Solicitè ſtude &amp; ante omnia hoc labora, &amp;c. <hi>Hieron in loc.</hi>
               </note> 2.
<hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Giue diligence to make your calling and election ſure.</hi> And,
<hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Shew the ſame diligence.</hi> And therefore <hi>S. Ierome</hi> readeth it, <hi>ſtudy carefully or diligently:</hi> and labour for this aboue all things, &amp;c. This then may bee our firſt inſtruction. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> That it ought to be the chiefe and principall care of a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> of the Word, to approue himſelfe vnto God. This was the endeuour of the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> as himſelfe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>As touching me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I paſſe very little to be iudged of you, or of mans iudgement: no, I iudge not mine owne ſelfe. For I know nothing by my ſelfe, yet am I not thereby iuſtified; but he that iudgeth me, is the Lord.</hi> Vpon which place <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus</hi> giueth this good note. The faithfulneſſe of a
<hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> of Chriſt, is not commended in that, that hee hee appeare faithfull to men, but that hee bee found faithfull of Chriſt the Lord. And therefore, ſaith he, this hee ſtudieth moſt, that from his heart hee may ſerue Chriſt, ſeeking nothing elſe but to aduance his Kingdome. And in another place
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16447:6"/>the <hi>Apostle</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2.</note>
               <hi>In declaration of the truth we approue our ſelues to euery mans conſcience in the ſight of God.</hi> And againe, <hi>In all things we approue our ſelues as the Miniſters of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.4.</note> The ſame care ought to bee in all other godly Miniſters. The reaſon is, becauſe euery good Miniſter is the ſeruant of God, and that after a ſpeciall manner, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith: <hi>God is my witneſſe, whom I ſerue in my Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>in the Goſpell of his Sonne:</hi> and in another place,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Hee counted me faithfull,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and put me in his ſeruice.</hi> Now, as euery good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant is carefull to approue himſelfe to his owne Maſter, aboue all other: ſo ſhould euery godly <hi>Miniſter</hi> deſire moſt of all to approue himſelfe to God. Yea, it is required of earthly ſeruants, that in the ſeruice they performe to their bodily maſters, they ſhould ſeeke the approbation of God, and therefore they are commanded,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ</hi> 6.7. <hi>Cel.</hi> 3.23.</note> 
               <hi>With good will to ſerue the Lord, and not men.</hi> And, <hi>Whatſoeuer they doe, to doe it heartily, as to the Lord, and not vnto men.</hi> Much more ſhould <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who doe immediately ſerue the Lord, in the worke of the miniſterie, ſeeke to approue themſelues vnto him. In the beginning of this Chapter,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3.</note> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calleth
<hi>Timotheus</hi> (and ſo all the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Word) <hi>a good Souldier of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Now, a Souldier hauing by oath bound himſelfe to his <hi>Captayne,</hi> or
<hi>Generall,</hi> endeuoureth ſo to carry himſelfe in the warres, as he may <hi>pleaſe him that hath choſen him to be a Souldier,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> In like manner, a <hi>Miniſter</hi> hauing giuen vp his name, and bound himſelfe to fight vnder the Banner, not of ſome earthly Captayne, as <hi>Alexander,</hi> or
<hi>Caeſar,</hi> or ſuch like, but of <hi>Christ Ieſus,</hi> the great <hi>Generall</hi> of heauen and earth, ought ſo to behaue himſelfe in all things that appertayne vnto his duety, as he may be approued and accepted of him that called him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> This doctrine, to make ſome vſe of it, ſerueth firſt, for the iuſt reproofe of thoſe, who not regarding the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of God, doe affect and hunt after the vaine and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular applauſe of men: gaping as greedily after it, as the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16447:7"/>
               <hi>Camaeleon</hi> doth after the ayre, which is her onely nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note n="*" place="margin">Pulchrum eſt monſtrari digi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, &amp; dicier hic eſt, <hi>Perſ. Sat.
1.</hi> AElian Var hiſt. lib. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> They count it a goodly matter, that men take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of them, and point at them for their gifts; yea, many times, though they be neuer ſo meane that doe it. As it is ſaid of <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> that he was filled with pride, when he heard the Water-bearers whiſper ſomething in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, as he paſſed by them. Now, he that is thus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, can neuer be ſincere in the execution of his miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. For he will meaſure all things by his owne eſtimation and credit, and will make all that he doth, yea, euen the doctrine that hee deliuereth, to ſerue to that end. And therefore, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> commending the ſinceritie of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie to the
<hi>Theſſalonians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.6.</note> taketh both God and them to witneſſe, that <hi>he neuer ſought praiſe of men, neither of them, nor of others:</hi> inſinuating, that if he had ſought praiſe and approbation with men, hee could not haue beene ſincere. For as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith well:<note place="margin">Controuerſ. lib.
<hi>5</hi>
               </note> He that ſeeketh after praiſe, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to haue himſelfe approued, and not the cauſe which he handleth; whereupon followeth this fault, that he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth many neceſſary things, while hee laboureth onely to make a faire ſhew. And hence is it, that vaine-glorious <hi>Ministers,</hi> are not the ſame men in their preaching, when they haue a great Auditory, as when they preach to a few. So that when wee ſee ſuch a man,<note place="margin">Sen. Epiſt. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> famous in the eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the people, applauded and commended whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hee commeth, wee haue cauſe to pitty him, and to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his eſtate, becauſe he cannot attayne to ſuch fauour by ſincere and faithfull dealing. I doe not denie, but a man may lawfully receiue that reuerent eſtimation, that is due to vertue and good deſerts. For it is the commandement of God, that they that are inferiour in gifts, ſhould honor thoſe whoſe gifts are more eminent, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.12. And it is agreeable to iuſtice, that they that are indued with more excellent gifts of God, and doe vſe them to the benefit of others, ſhould in thankefulneſſe receiue ſome recompence. Now, what better recompence can be giuen them, then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16447:7"/>honor and due reſpect? Beſides, it is very profitable. For they that haue gifts in any meaſure, are hereby excited and ſtirred vp to ſtriue to a greater excellency. And the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that is done vnto them, doth procure them authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with others, and cauſe them to be had in higher repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and ſo their paines and diligence doth the more good. And therefore, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth not ſay, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed that reuerence and honor that was giuen to him and his <hi>Apoſtleſhip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.14.</note> though he acknowledge that the <hi>Galatians receiued him as an Angell of God, yea, as Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> but onely he ſaith, he affected it not, he ſought not after it am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly, as too many doe, which is the greateſt vanitie in the world.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi>
10.18.</note> For, as he, <hi>that prayſeth himſelfe, is not allowed</hi> (as the
<hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith) ſo neither is he allowed, that by this meanes is fondly praiſed of men, <hi>but hee whom the Lord prayſeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> Secondly, it ſerueth to admoniſh euery one of vs, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour aboue all things for the Lords approbation in our miniſterie, that we may <hi>be Paſtors according to his heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.15.</note> as the Lord himſelfe ſaith: For this end, firſt, it is required of vs, that we be faithfull in the diſcharge of our dueties. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> exhorteth earthly ſeruants,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi>
2.10.</note> 
               <hi>to ſhew all good faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> vnto their bodily Maſters. Much more muſt wee bee faithfull, that are Gods <hi>Stewards,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi>
4.1.2.</note> to whom he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the diſpenſation of his holy myſteries: whereupon, faith <hi>Luther,</hi> Let euery man bee faithfull in his miniſterie. Let him not ſeeke his owne glory, Let him not reſt in the vaine applauſe of the fooliſh multitude: but let this be his greateſt care, that he may performe his worke well, that is, that hee may purely preach the Goſpell. But our faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe muſt eſpecially appeare in this, that we labour to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſciples vnto Chriſt. We may not be like thoſe falſe Teachers, which the
<hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaketh of,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.30.</note> 
               <hi>To draw Diſciples after our ſelues,</hi> that is, to make Sects, and cauſe men to giue vp their names to vs. But all our endeuour muſt bee to bring men to Chriſt. And this is inſinuated in the
<hi>commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:16447:8"/>which Chriſt giueth his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi>
28.19.</note> and in them the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> that ſucceed them,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> namely, <hi>To goe and teach all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> where the word ſignifieth to make them <hi>Diſciples.</hi> As all the gaine of earthly ſeruants doth redound vnto their Maſters, and not to themſelues: ſo the ſoules that we gaine by our preaching, ſhould redound vnto God. And therefore,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.19.20.</note> when the
<hi>Iewes</hi> began to make account of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> both for the auſteritie of his life, and for the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of his preaching, and the rareneſſe of his baptiſme; he would by no meanes ſuffer them to be too highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited of him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi>
26.27.</note> but laboureth to make them acknowledge Chriſt, whom hee ſo farre preferred before himſelfe, as hee confeſſeth, hee was not worthy to <hi>vnlooſe the latchet of his ſhoo.</hi> And when his owne Diſciples began to dote of him more then was fit, and went about to breed ſome emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in him againſt our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt,</hi> becauſe he alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to <hi>baptize,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.26.28 30.</note> 
               <hi>and all men came to him,</hi> hee telleth them in plaine termes, that it was meet they ſhould doe ſo. And as for himſelfe, he had told them that he was onely a fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſent before him;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.2.</note> and ſaith he, <hi>He muſt increaſe, but I must decreaſe.</hi> Yea afterwards, hee ſendeth them alſo to Chriſt, that they might know him to be the only true <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias,</hi> and ſo alſo become followers of him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt in all our miniſterie chiefly ayme at the glory of God, and the ſaluation of the people, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to our charge. It is the generall duety of all Chriſtians, in all their actions to propound the glory of God, as their chiefe and principall ſcope.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoeuer yee doe</hi> (ſaith the
<hi>Apoſtle) doe all to the glory of God.</hi> Much more ſhould <hi>Miniſters</hi> make the glory of God the principall end of all their miniſteriall dueties. And indeed, the glory of all our actions is wholly due to the Lord, who worketh whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is wrought by vs. We are but inſtruments in the Lords hand, and therefore, we cannot arrogate any thing to our ſelues without preiudice to him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jſa.</hi> 10.15.</note> 
               <hi>Shall the axe</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Prophet) boast it ſelfe againſt him that heweth therewith? or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16447:8"/>ſhall the Saw exalt it ſelfe againſt him that moueth it?</hi> If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee ſee any good effect wrought by our miniſterie, let vs ſay with <hi>Dauid, Not vnto vs, O Lord, not vnto vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.1.</note> 
               <hi>but vnto thy Name giue the glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the ſaluation of the people, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> vſeth it as an argument to perſwade <hi>Timotheus,</hi> to be diligent and conſtant in the diſcharge of his duety.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>Take heede vnto thy ſelfe,</hi> ſaith he,
<hi>and vnto learning; continue therein: for in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, thou ſhalt ſaue both thy ſelfe and them that heare thee.</hi> As if hee ſhould haue ſaid,<note place="margin">Calu. in locum.</note> Let them that are deſirous of vaine-glorie, pleaſe themſelues with their owne ambition: let them applaude themſelues in the ſubtilties of their wit; let it be ſufficient for thee, to bend thy ſtudy to the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of thine owne and the peoples ſaluation. Thus if we ſet our ſelues to bee approued vnto God, the Lord that knoweth our ſinceritie, will not be wanting to reward vs liberally, and that euen in this life,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi>
4.14.</note> making <hi>the Spirit of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to reſt vponvs,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> calleth it. To which purpoſe <hi>Luther</hi> hath a good ſaying: If a mans worke bee right, let him be ſure that hee ſhall neuer want glory nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with God, nor with men. As wee ſee by experience, that they that ſet themſelues conſcionably to performe the dueties of their calling, the Lord doth ſooner or later cauſe them to bee eſteemed and had in reuerence of men, yea many times of ſuch as are enemies to the <hi>Goſpell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen.
<hi>Epiſt.</hi> 80.</note> The Heathen man could ſay, that glory is the ſhadow of vertue, which will accompany men whether they will or no. But as the ſhaddow ſometimes goeth before the bodie, and ſometimes followeth after: ſo glory is ſometimes before vs, and preſenteth it ſelfe to our view; ſometimes it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth behinde vs, and is the greater, by how much it is the later, when enuie is ceaſed, namely after our death. But without all queſtion, howſoeuer it pleaſeth the Lord to deale with vs in this life: yet at the great day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>When the chiefe Shepheard ſhall appeare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>we ſhall receiue an incorruptible Crowne of glory.</hi> Then our <hi>Maſter Chriſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16447:9"/>Ieſus,</hi> when hee ſhall come to call vs to account for the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents and gifts which he hath giuen vs, and ſhall finde that wee haue imployed them to the glory of his Name, and the good of his Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 5.21.</note> ſhall ſay vnto vs, <hi>It is well done, thou good and faithfull ſeruant: enter into thy Maſters ioy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſt of all, here is alſo an admonition for all the hearers of the Word, that they ſuffer their <hi>Miniſters</hi> to performe this duetie. There is a ſecret corruption in moſt men, they would haue a Miniſter to ſpeake to their humours, and to ſooth them vp in whatſoeuer they do. If they ſay the Crow is white,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 30 10.</note> they would haue the Miniſter to ſay ſo too. They cannot indure that hee ſhould <hi>propheſie right things vnto them,</hi> but would haue him to ſpeake <hi>flattering things,</hi> as the
<hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith of the people in his time. But, as hath beene ſaid alreadie, The
<hi>Miniſter</hi> is the ſeruant of Chriſt, to whom onely he ought to approoue himſelfe, and of whom onely hee ought to labour to draw men to bee followers, and therefore, he muſt adminiſter and diſpenſe the Word indifferently vnto all, not caring whom he pleaſeth or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſeth, ſo he may pleaſe God. What meſſage ſoeuer the Lord putteth into his mouth, how harſh ſoeuer it be, hee muſt deliuer it faithfully, though all the world be offended at it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ky.</hi> 1.17.</note> As the Lord charged the <hi>Prophet Ieremy; Speake vnto them all that I command thee, be not afraid of their faces, leſt I deſtroy thee before them.</hi> The <hi>Miniſter,</hi> you ſee, muſt deale faithfully in the Lords buſmeſſe, euen vpon paine of his high diſpleaſure.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi>
23.12.</note> 
               <hi>Balaam</hi> that falſe prophet could ſay, <hi>Muſt I not take heede to ſpeake that, which the Lord bath put into my mouth?</hi> Much more ought a godly
<hi>miniſter</hi> to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that way, that though hee might gaine neuer ſo much by flattering,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.18.</note> yet hee muſt <hi>not goe beyond the Word of the Lord, to doe leſſe or more:</hi> hee muſt not giue <hi>titles to men,</hi> nor cauſeleſſely commend them without deſert, <hi>leſt his Maker reproue him,</hi> as
<hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>Iob</hi> 32.22. Yea the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>If he ſhould goe about to pleaſe men, hee were not the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of Chriſt.</hi> If he ſhould apply his doctrine to mens hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16447:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>mours and affections, the Lord would neuer approue him. And therefore all this being ſo, you muſt giue your <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> leaue to diſcharge their duties in all ſinceritie, and not bee offended, though at Gods Commandement, they doe ſomewhat ſharpely reprooue your ſinnes. For as the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> ſaid of obedience, ſo may wee ſay in this caſe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 4.19.</note> 
               <hi>Whether it bee right in the ſight of God, to pleaſe you rather then God, iudge ye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Workeman.</hi> The ſame word is vſed in the parable of the Vineyard, <hi>Math.</hi>
20.1. and there is tranſlated <hi>labourers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And ſo it is vſed, 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.10. where the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth, that if
<hi>there were any that would not worke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>hee ſhould not eate.</hi> From whence ariſeth this next inſtruction:<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> That the Calling of a <hi>Miniſter</hi> is a painefull and laborious calling, and he that would approue himſelfe and his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie vnto God, hee muſt be a
<hi>workeman.</hi> This the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> confirmeth in many other places. Exhorting the
<hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians</hi> to a reuerent and due eſtimation of their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Know them that labour among you, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5
12.</note> And in an other place, <hi>The Elders,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that rule well,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>are worthy of double honour; eſpecially they which labour in the Word and Doctrine.</hi> In both which places, the word there vſed,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> doth ſignifie to labour vnto wearineſſe. In like manner, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Timotheus</hi> to the performance of his duety, hee bids him, <hi>Watch in all things, doe the worke of an Euangeliſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5.</note>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And, deſcribing the office of a faithfull <hi>Miniſter,</hi> he ſaith,
<hi>If any man deſire the office of a Biſhop,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi>
3.1.</note> 
               <hi>he deſireth a worthy worke.</hi> Wherevpon <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Epiſcopatus nomeneſt operis, non honoris.</note> The office of a
<hi>Biſhop</hi> is a name of labour, not of honor: that a man may know that he is no
<hi>Biſhop,</hi> that would bear rule, but would doe no good. According to that ſpeech of our
<hi>Sauiour, Math.</hi> 9.37. <hi>Surely the harueſt is great, but the labourers are few: wherefore pray the Lord of the harueſt, that he would ſend forth labourers into his harueſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De ciu. Dei li. <hi>19</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi> De vit. &amp; morib. Cleric. Serm. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Where the ſame word is vſed that is in this place. Whereunto agreeth that ſaying of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that the office of a <hi>Miniſter</hi> is rather a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16447:10"/>then an honor.<note place="margin">Declam.</note> And <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, Great is the place of <hi>Miniſters</hi> in the Kingdome of God: but yet there is no ſmall labour belonging vnto them. So then, though the calling of a <hi>Miniſter</hi> bee an high and honourable calling, yet it is not a calling of eaſe, but of labour. And though the worke of the miniſtery bee a worthy and an excellent worke: yet it is a worke, yea and that a painfull worke.</p>
            <p>Now the worke and labour of a Miniſter conſiſteth in theſe three things:<note place="margin">Quandoque pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum nouit, nemo docere poteſt.</note> Firſt, in priuate ſtudie: Secondly, in fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent prayer: Thirdly, in diligent preaching of Gods Word.</p>
            <p>For the firſt: a faithfull Miniſter muſt labor in his priuate ſtudie, that he may bee furniſhed with knowledge, for the better diſcharge of his dutie. Hee muſt firſt learne by ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, before hee can bee fit to teach others. For no man can teach that, whereof hee is ignorant himſelfe. The <hi>Moone</hi> and the <hi>Starres</hi> firſt receiue light themſelues from the <hi>Sun,</hi> before they giue light to the inferiour creatures. So muſt the
<hi>Miniſter</hi> firſt be inlightened himſelfe with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the holy Scriptures, before he can inſtruct others in the ſame. No man (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) preſumeth to teach any Art, vnleſſe by diligent meditation he haue firſt learned it himſelfe. But the regiment of ſoules is the Art of all Arts, For this cauſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.
6, 7.</note> the <hi>Prophet Iſaiah</hi> had <hi>his lips touched with a coale from the Altar,</hi> before his commiſſion was renued to preach to the <hi>Iewes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 24.45.</note> And our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> firſt <hi>opened the vnderſtandings</hi> of his Diſciples, <hi>that they might vnderſtand the Scriptures:</hi> before hee would ſend them forth to preach the <hi>Goſpell:</hi> and commanded them beſides to tarrie at <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 49.</note> till they ſhould be endued <hi>with power from an high.</hi> To teach vs, that howſoeuer this extraordinarie and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate inſpiring of men from heauen, be now ceaſed: yet by ordinarie ſtudie, a man muſt bee furniſhed with knowledge, before hee can bee a ſufficient teacher and inſtructer of others. And this doth the <hi>Prophet</hi> require of euery <hi>Prieſt</hi> in the time of the Law.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>The Prieſts lippes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16447:10"/>ſhould preſerue knowledge, and they ſhould ſeeke the law at his mouth: for he is the meſſenger of the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> Wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſaith <hi>Gualter, Ministers</hi> muſt keepe the law of truth, and preſerue the knowledge thereof, as it were in a ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, that from thence they may bring foorth all things, that tend to the edification of the Church.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim</hi> 3.2. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2.</note> And the
<hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> likewiſe requireth of the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> that they be <hi>apt and able to teach others?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyprian, ad Pomp.</note> To which purpoſe <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> hath a good ſaying: A Miniſter muſt not onely teach, but alſo learne himſelfe, becauſe he teacheth better that learneth euery day, and profiteth, in learning better things. And this was ſignified in the myſticall apparell of the
<hi>Prieſts</hi> where the Lord commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to put <hi>in the Brest-plate of iudgement, the Vrim and the Thummim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.30.</note> 
               <hi>which ſhall bee vpon Aarons heart.</hi> Whereby was ſhaddowed out the cleare knowledge of heauenly things, wherewith the Miniſter ſhould be ended. A Miniſter therefore muſt giue himſelfe night and day to the ſtudie of Gods Word.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Sencca</hi> ſaith of himſelfe, that he ſo bent and ſettled himſelfe to the ſtudy of
<hi>morall Philoſophie,</hi> that he ſuffered no day to paſſe from him in idleneſſe, but applied part of the night to his ſtudy, that hee did not giue himſelfe to ſleepe, till hee was ouercome with it, and when his eyes were wearied, and ready to fall downe with watching, yet ſtill he kept them in worke. And it is reported of <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> that while he was ſearching out the nature of things, he neuer vſed to ſleepe, but with an iron ball in his hand, hanging ouer a braſen panne, that when it ſhould fall out of his hand, the ſound of it might awake him. If theſe men were thus painefull, in labouring to attaine to the knowledge of
<hi>Philoſophy,</hi> for their owne priuate contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation: how much more painefull ſhould a Miniſter be in the ſtudy of the Word of God, whereby hee may be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to teach others?
<hi>'Dauid</hi> maketh it the propertie of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery godly man, <hi>to meditate in the Law of the Lord night and day: Pſal.</hi> 1.2. And our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> commandeth all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16447:11"/>Chriſtians in generall,<note place="margin">Iohn <hi>5.39.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to ſearch the Scriptures.</hi> Much more is a Miniſter bound to doe it, becauſe the chiefe end of his calling, is not onely the priuate informing of himſelfe in knowledge of God and his will, but alſo and chiefly, <hi>the gathering together of the Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>and the edification of the body of Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith: For this cauſe, our <hi>Sauiour</hi> compareth a <hi>Miniſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.52.</note> whom hee calleth <hi>a Scribe, which is taught vnto the Kingdome of heauen,</hi> vnto <hi>an houſe-holder, which bringeth forth out of his treaſury, things both new &amp; old.</hi> His heart ſhould be euen a ſtore-houſe of knowledge, and gracious inſtructions, he ſhould neuer be vnprepared, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euery occaſion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 13.15.</note> to vſe ſome <hi>word of exhortation to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may ſerue, firſt, to reprooue two ſorts of <hi>Miniſters.</hi> Firſt, ſuch as take vpon them <hi>to be teachers of others,</hi> and yet <hi>ſtand in need themſelues to be taught the firſt principles of the word of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12.</note> As there be many that enter into the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie for maintenance ſake, making that high calling their laſt refuge, who for want of knowledge, haue no meaſure of abilitie to diſcharge their dutie. Theſe expoſe themſelues and their calling vnto contempt and reproch. For as one ſaith well: What can the multitude admire in them, if they ſee no more in them, nay peraduenture, not ſo much as they find in themſelues?<note place="margin">Pet. Mart. de dignit. miniſt. Ex Mal. <hi>2.7.</hi>
               </note> A Miniſter ſhould bee both able and willing to anſwere to all things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to ſaluation. Let them therefore diſcharge this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, let them be interpreters of the will of God, or elſe let them ceaſe to be <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Church, and the Lords meſſengers.<note place="margin">Bern. Declam.</note> And therefore
<hi>Bernard</hi> hath a good ſaying: How can ignorance excuſe him, that profeſſeth himſelfe to be an inſtructer of the vnlearned, and a teacher of them that lacke diſcretion? For what danger is there, when as the ſhepheard findeth no paſture, the guide is ignorant of the way, and the meſſenger knoweth not the will of his maſter?</p>
            <p>Secondly, they alſo are here reproued, that haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16447:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>and other good giſts, but doe not <hi>ſtirre them vp,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.</note> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> exhorteth <hi>Timotheus,</hi> that is, doe not by paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtudy and continuall vſe, labour to increaſe them, but rather ſuffer them to gather ruſt, and become vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Hence it commeth to paſle, that either they preach very ſeldome; or when they doe preach, they make ſuch cold collations, and bring forth ſuch flaſhy and vnſauory ſtuffe, as can neuer profit nor benefit their happines. It was ſaid of the Heathen Orator,<note place="margin">Cael. Rhodig. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap.
<hi>13.</hi>
               </note> that his orations did ſmell of the candle. Much more ſhould a Chriſtian miniſter deſire to haue his Sermons which he deliuereth to Gods people, to ſmell of ſtudy, and of painefull diligence. For if there be a curſe denounced againſt him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 48.10.</note> 
               <hi>that doth the worke of the Lord negligently:</hi> much more ſhall he be accurſed, that ſhal be negligent and careleſſe in the performance of this great and waightie worke of the Miniſterie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this may ſerue to excite and ſtirre vs vp to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and painefulneſſe in our ſtudies. Wee ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that charge which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> giueth to
<hi>Timothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> as if it had beene giuen to euery one of our ſelues: <hi>Gine attendance toreading, to exhortation, and to doctrine:</hi> that is,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi>
4.13.</note> we muſt ſo apply our ſelues to the reading and ſtudying of the Scriptures, as out of them we may be able to gather exhortation &amp; doctrine, for the inſtruction and edification of Gods people. For as <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith vpon that place, What ſhall Paſtors teach others, if they bee not diligent in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning themſelues? Againe, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, <hi>Deſpiſe not the gift that is inthee, &amp;c. verſ.</hi> 14. God would not haue the Talents which he hath giuen vs, to periſh, or to be hid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably vnder the ground. A gaine, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 15. <hi>Theſe things exerciſe, and giue thy ſelfe vnto them, that it may be ſeene how thou profiteſt, &amp;c.</hi> This ſhould be the continuall practice, this ſhould bee the daily occupation, this ſhould bee the chiefe buſineſſe of euery godly Miniſter, to labour by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ſtudie, to increaſe the gift which God hath giuen him. For this cauſe, he muſt carefully auoide euery thing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16447:12"/>that might hinder him from the performance of this duty. And firſt of all, he muſt take heed, that he be not too much giuen to the world:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi>
2.4.</note> 
               <hi>No man that warreth,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, entangleth himſelfe with the affaires of this life.</hi> If the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> would not be troubled with
<hi>ſeruing of tables,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 6.2, 3, 4.</note> that is, with care for the poore, which yet was a godly and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous worke: but appointed others to that buſineſſe, that they might more freely giue themſelues <hi>continually to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and to the miniſtration of the word:</hi> much leſſe ſhould a Miniſter be encumbred with worldly buſineſſe. For if the <hi>buying of farmes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 14.18,
19.</note> 
               <hi>and prouing of oxen,</hi> and the vſe of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe doe hinder men from hearing the Word: much more will they hinder a <hi>miniſter</hi> from ſtudying of the Word. Our
<hi>Sautour Chriſt</hi> would haue a <hi>miniſter</hi> to bee <hi>taught to the Kangdome of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. <hi>13.52.</hi>
               </note> as hath been ſaid. That muſt be his ſcope which he muſt chiefly aime at. Let other men be skilfull in buying of cattell, or in ordering of farmes, the chiefe skill of a Miniſter ſhould bee this, that hee bee taught to the Kingdome of God. And as wee haue heard, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> commandeth <hi>Timotheus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe things exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and giue thy ſelfe to them.</hi> The exerciſe of a <hi>Miniſter</hi> muſt not bee in worldly buſineſſe, but in the ſtudy of the Word of God. And indeed the office of a <hi>Miniſter</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the whole man, and hee performeth no ſmall matter, that is any way able to diſcharge the ſame. For as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>2.16.</hi> De confid. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> If an ordinarie ſeruant, ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi> to <hi>Eugensus</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> bee not able both to keep the cattel, and alſo to waite at the table; how canſt thou by thy ſelfe attend all theſe things? And indeed, the care of worldly things quencheth the zeale of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that hee cannot ſo feruently attend his ſtudy as hee ought. For as a riuer, that is diuided into many ſtreames, hath a great deale leſſe force, then when it runneth in one current: ſo the minde of a Miniſter diſtracted with world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſineſſe, cannot bee carried to the diſcharge of his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, with that liuelyhood and chearefulneſſe that is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16447:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>If a Brooke, ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> can run out into the field,<note place="margin">Bern. vbi ſupra.</note> and not hurt the Corne, then mayſt thou meddle with theſe things without wounding thy mind. And hereof we haue too much experience: For euen as many ſeruants, hauing got ſome competent ſtocke vnder a good maſter, doe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſo much vpon the increaſe of it, as they neglect the old care of their maſter: ſo many Miniſters, hauing by Gods bleſſing enriched themſelues, become altogether careleſſe of their dutie. And this is it, that giueth occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to many prophane perſons to thinke, that it is beſt for Miniſters to be kept vnder by liuing in want, becauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times it is ſeene, that when they grow rich, they waxe idle.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a Miniſter muſt take heede, that he giue not himſelfe to keepe company in Ale-houſes and Tauernes, and ſuch like lewd and vngodly places. I would to God there were not many,<note place="margin">Iuuat. impalleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere charlis, ſed pictis.</note> that are a great deale oftner in the Ale-houſe, then in their Studies; and that handle a paire of Chards more, then they doe the Booke of God. And I would this were only the fault of ſome baſe perſons in the Miniſterie, &amp; that there were not ſome, who otherwiſe are of excellent gifts, and haue a good dexteritie in preaching, are as frequent in Ale-houſes, as the greateſt ſwaggerers in the Country. This is the greateſt diſgrace of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie that can be. And it were to be wiſhed, that they that haue authoritie, would take notice of it, and ſet themſelues to redreſſe it. It drowneth and vtterly quencheth the gifts of God in men, and maketh them become altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable. And this the Heathen men did know, and therefore were carefull to preuent it.<note place="margin">Cael. Rhodig. lib. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> The Prieſts of Egypt were forbidden to drinke of the water of <hi>Nilus,</hi> becauſe it would make them fat and groſſe. And doe we not ſee the ſame effect in thoſe Miniſters that frequent the Ale-houſe, that they heaue and puffe vp their bodies in a deformed manner? which doubtleſſe cannot but dull the ſpirits: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the old prouerb: A fat belly ſeldome begets a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16447:13"/>fine wit. Let all Miniſters therefore be carefull to auoide theſe prophane and ſcandalous courſes. Let them bee as loth to come into an Ale-houſe, as into a Peſt-houſe: and let them ſequeſter and retire themſelues into their Studies, that ſo they may bee furniſhed with knowledge, and may diſcharge their duties more profitably to others, and more comfortably to themſelues.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing, wherein the labour and worke of a <hi>Minister</hi> conſiſteth, is in feruent and ear<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſt prayer to God for his people.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi>
9.25.26.</note> Thus did <hi>Moſes</hi> pray earneſtly to God for the people of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> to pacifie his wrath, which by their ſinnes they had prouoked.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.23.</note> Thus did <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> promiſe, neuer to giue ouer this dutie for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: <hi>God forbid,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>that I ſhould ſinne againſt the Lord, and ceaſe praying for you.</hi> Where wee ſee, that it is a grieuous ſinne for a
<hi>Miniſter</hi> to neglect this dutie. And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> PAVI in all his
<hi>Epiſtles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. <hi>1.6.</hi> &amp; <hi>3.14.</hi> Col.
<hi>1.9.</hi> &amp;c.</note> maketh menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his prayers, which without ceaſing, hee conceiued in the behalfe of the people to whom hee writeth. And great reaſon there is, why a Miniſter ſhould performe this worke. For as the Husbandman deſireth two things of the Lord, one that hee may haue a ſeaſonable time to ſowe his ſeede; another, that when it is ſowne, it may bee watred with the Deaw, and Shewres of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that it may grow and increaſe: ſo ſhould a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter before his preaching, pray to God, that firſt, the Word of God may bee aptly conceiued, and then rightly deliuered by him, and well ſowne in the hearts of his hearers. And after his preaching, hee muſt pray for a bleſsing vpon it, that it may take roote downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and beare fruite vpward. Hee muſt, as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith well, commend to God, both his owne tongue and the hearts of his hearers. The neglect of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is the cauſe, why many mens Miniſterie is ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable. For while they ſeeke to vent their owne gift onely, and not to glorifie God, they are both them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16447:13"/>more ſhallow in the vnderſtanding of Gods will, and alſo their Miniſterie hath not that bleſſing, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it might. But I will not proſecute this point any further.</p>
            <p>The laſt and greateſt worke of a <hi>Minister,</hi> conſiſteth in painefull and diligent preaching. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> PAVL impoſeth this vpon <hi>Timotheus</hi> with a great and waightie charge. <hi>I charge thee before God,</hi> ſaith hee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Tim.
<hi>4.1.2.</hi> Gorran in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum illum.</note> 
               <hi>and before the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which ſhall iudge the quicke and dead at his appearing, and in has Kingdome, Preach the Word; bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, &amp;c.</hi> That is, Preach inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and diligently: in ſeaſon, in reſpect of them that are pleaſed with the Word: and out of ſeaſon, in regard of them that are diſpleaſed with it, and to whom it is a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. And though in reſpect of them, thou mayeſt ſeeme vnſeaſonable; yet thou ſhalt deale ſeaſonably. Or as <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin</hi> expoundeth it: This importunitie may bee referred both to the Paſtor, and to the people. To the Paſtor, that hee doe not onely at his owne houres, as may be conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for himſelfe, apply the office of teaching, but ſparing no labour nor trouble, he muſt euen enforce himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. In reſpect of the people, this diligence is vnſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, whileſt they that are dull and heauie, are ſtirred vp and excited; and they that are readie to goe out of the way, are ſtayed by ſtrong hand. Or as <hi>Aretius</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth: Preach the Word at all times. In ſeaſon: That is, when occaſion doth offer it ſelfe. Out of ſeaſon, when, in the iudgement of the fleſh, it may ſeeme inconuenient, in reſpect of preſent danger. This is the charge impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon euerie <hi>Miniſter.</hi> And as all profeſsions and trades are knowne by their proper workes: ſo the proper worke of a
<hi>Miniſter,</hi> is to preach the Word. And therefore they are called <hi>Paſtors and Teachers;</hi> becauſe by preaching,<note place="margin">Epheſ. <hi>4.11.</hi>
               </note> they ſhould feede and teach the people. And this they are bound to doe, euen by the neceſsitie of their calling. As the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:16447:14"/>ſaith,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16.</note> 
               <hi>Neceſſitie is laid vpon me, and woe is vnto me, if I preach not the Goſpell.</hi> Yea, they muſt giue account to God, for all the people committed to their charge. So ſaith the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle: They watch for your ſoules, as they that muſt giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi>
13.17.</note> And this the Lord told the <hi>Prophet</hi> EZECHIEL: <hi>O ſonne of man, I haue made thee a watch-man to the houſe of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech</hi> 33.7,
8.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. When I ſhall ſay to the wicked, O wicked man, thou ſhalt die the death: if thou doeſt not ſpeake and admoniſh the wicked of his way; that wicked man ſhall die for his iniquitie, but his bloud will I require at thine hand.</hi> If the caſe be thus, that a Miniſter ſtand charged with euery ſoule that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vnto him, ſo as if any miſcarry through his neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, his life muſt goe for theirs, then it ſtandeth him in hand, to look carefully to the diſcharge of his dutie. Again, the loue that we owe to <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> ought to moue vs hereunto. And therfore, when our <hi>Sauier</hi> reſtored
<hi>Peter</hi> againe to his paſtorall charge, after his former deniall: he vſeth this as an argument to perſwade him to diligence therein. Which he repeateth three ſeuerall times.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 21.15, 16, 17.</note> SIMON, <hi>the ſonne of Iona, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt thou me more then theſe? then feede my lambs, feede my ſheepe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi>
5.14.</note> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſeth, that the <hi>loue of Chriſt conſtrained him</hi> to take ſuch paines as he did. Laſt of al, the loue of our people ſhould preuaile with vs, to vſe al meanes poſsible to further their ſaluation. As the Apoſtle hath giuen vs a notable example in his owne practice:<note place="margin">Rom.
<hi>10.1.</hi> Phil. <hi>1.8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>mine hearts deſire and prayer to God for Iſrael is, that they might be ſaued.</hi> And in another place, <hi>God is my record, how I long after you all from the very heart roote in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.15. <hi>&amp;</hi>
               </note> And againe, <hi>I will moſt gladly beſtow, and will be beſtowed for your ſoules.</hi> And if this affection be in a man, it will cauſe him to omit no dutie,<note place="margin">11.2.</note> that he may <hi>preſent his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a pure virgine to Chriſt.</hi> And the rather, becauſe hee knoweth, that <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> hath redeemed them with no leſſe price then <hi>with his owne bloud.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28.</note> And therefore, as they are moſt deare and precious vnto
<hi>Chriſt:</hi> ſo ſhould they alſo bee vnto the <hi>Miniſter</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> This then is the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16447:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>maine dutie of a Miniſter, wherein he is to be moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent. As that Reuerend <hi>Father, Biſhop Iewel,</hi> doth ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly vrge it in one of his Sermons. This is our office,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11.</note> ſaith he, this we take vpon vs, this we profeſſe, and except we doe this, we doe nothing. It is not enough for vs, to know I cannot tell whatlearning. The Deuils peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture know more then any of vs all. It belongeth to a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, not ſo much to haue learned many things, as to haue taught much. Let vs bee aſhamed, that euen the meaneſt and baſeſt men, as Coblers and Porters do that that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to them, and we that ought to giue light to al others, are idle and doe nothing.</p>
            <p>But it will be obiected: Is not diſtinct and plaine rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Scriptures ſufficient? I anſwere, that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is very neceſſarie, and of great vſe, both to acquaint the people with the phraſe of the Scripture, and courſe of the ſtorie; and alſo to prepare them, and fit them the better to the hearing of Sermons: and therefore, God forbid, that any man ſhould derogate from it. But yet I muſt ſay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that in an ordinarie time, reading is not ſufficient to bring the people to ſaluation without preaching. And this the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> prooueth plaincly,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>and</hi> 4.1, 2.</note> where hee ſaith, that <hi>the whole Scripture is giuen by inſpiration of God, and is profitable to teach, to improoue, to correct, and to inſtruct in righteouſues, that the man of Godmay be abſolute, being made perfect vnto all good workes.</hi> And then immediately he addeth that charge which we heard before: <hi>I charge thee therefore,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> preach the Word.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Caluin</hi> giueth this note: The inference that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> maketh, is diligently to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, becauſe he doth plainely ioyne the Scriptures with preaching. For hauing intreated of the profit of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, he doth not onely inferre, that all men muſt therfore read them, but that teachers muſt adminiſter the ſame.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi>
4.13.</note> And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> commandeth <hi>Timotheus to giue attendance not to reading onely,</hi> but alſo <hi>to exhortation and doctrine.</hi> And the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> hauing taught vs,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23, 25.</note> that the <hi>Word of God is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16447:15"/>that immortall ſeede of our new birth:</hi> he addeth, <hi>and this is the Word which is preached among you.</hi> Plainely giuing vs to vnderſtand, that for the effecting of this bleſſed work of regeneration, it is neceſſarie that the Word of God be preached. And therefore, this was obſerued in the Church of the Iewes from time to time. In the time of
<hi>Nehemiab,</hi> before the comming of our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt,</hi> it is ſaid of
<hi>Ezra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nebem. <hi>3.4, 5, 8.</hi>
               </note> that hee <hi>ſtood vpon a Pulpit of wood, which hee had made for the preaching, and being aboue all the people, hee opened the booke of the Law before them, and hee and his aſſiſtants read in it diſtinctly, and gaue the ſenſe, and cauſed them to vnderſtand the reading.</hi> What can be ſpoken more plainely then this? It is euident then, that as reading was by no meanes excluded, ſo it was neuer vſed alone in the Church, but was ioyned with preaching. And this our Sauiour Chriſt practiſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 4.16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21.</note> who comming to
<hi>Nazaret, and entring into the Synagogue on the Sabbath day, he ſtood vp to reade;</hi> and hauing read a portion of Scripture, <hi>he cloſed the booke, and ſate downe, and preached vnto them,</hi> out of that which hee had read.<note place="margin">Act. <hi>15.21.</hi> Onus ipſis Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis formidan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</note> And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> IAMES affirmeth, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was not onely <hi>read in their ſynagogues in euerie citie,</hi> but alſo <hi>preached euery Sabbath day.</hi> Furthermore, the worke of a <hi>Miniſter</hi> is a worke of great difficultie.
<hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> calleth it a burden dreadfull to the very Angels. And <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith, it is a buſineſſe of rare and excellent vertue, farre aboue the abilitie of man. Yea, the
<hi>Apoſtle</hi> PAVL himſelfe, though he were extraordinarily furniſhed with gifts from heauen; yet conſidering the waightineſſe of the dutie, hee cryeth out, <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. And where the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calleth the worke of a <hi>Biſhop, a worthy worke:</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Caluin</hi> vpon that place obſerueth well, that hee putteth vs in minde, that it is no common or ordinarie worke: For, ſaith he, when hee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it a worthy worke, hee alludeth to that old prouerbe, ſo often repeated of PLATO, that <hi>excellent things are hard.</hi> And ſo concludeth, that it is a laborious and a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16447:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>charge. Now I hope it will eaſily bee granted, that there can be no ſuch difficulty in the bare reading of the Word. But for further euidence of this point, let vs ſee a little wherein this difficultie conſiſteth. Firſt then, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry framing and compiling of a Sermon, is a matter of no ſmall labour. It requireth great skill, for a man to draw out of the bottomleſſe <hi>Ocean</hi> of the holy Scriptures, ſuch inſtructions as may ſerue to the edification of the hearers; then to diſpoſe them in an apt and fit methode; and laſt of all, to vtter and deliuer the ſame in ſuch manner, as the people may vnderſtand them, wee may more truely ſay of this, then the Heathen <hi>Orator</hi> ſaid of his facultie in pleading; It is a greater matter then men ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginc.</p>
            <p>Againe, that which the <hi>Miniſter</hi> muſt labour to effect and performe by his Miniſtery, doth plainely prooue how hard and difficult a thing it is. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> deſeribing the properties of a good <hi>Miniſter, Tit.</hi> 1.9. he ſaith,<note place="margin">De doct. Chr. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> he muſt <hi>bee able both to exhort with wholeſome doctrine, and to improoue them that ſay againſt it.</hi> Whereunto agreeth that ſpeech of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> where he calleth a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> a maintainer of the truth, and a ſubduer of falſhood, a defender of the right faith, and a vanquiſher of errour. And <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De conſider. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> writing to
<hi>Eugenius,</hi> telleth him, that it is his dutie to do his vttermoſt endeauour, that the vnbeleeuers may bee conuerted to the faith, that they that are conuerted, may not bee turned away, that they that are turned away, may returne againe, that they that are peruerted, may be diſpoſed to vertue and honeſty, and that they that are ſubuerted, may bee called againe to the truth. Now hee that ſhall goe about to doe any of theſe things, ſhall finde to bee workes of greater difficultie, then can be effected by bare reading.</p>
            <p>Laſt of al, if reading were ſufficient, and if there were no more required in a
<hi>Minister,</hi> to what purpoſe did our religious and deuoute forefathers found and erect ſo

<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16447:16"/>many famous <hi>Vniuerſities,</hi> to be nurſeries of learning? what vſe is there of the knowledge of arts and tongues, which cannot be attained without great paines and induſtrie? and to what end ſerue the learned writings of ſo many worthy ancient fathers? A man without any of theſe helpes, may be ſufficiently furniſhed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jſa.</hi> 50.4.</note> and inabled to reade the Word. He needeth not <hi>the tongue of the learned</hi> (which yet is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite in him, that would <hi>know to miniſter a word in time to him that is wearie:</hi> that is, would comfort an afflicted conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which
<hi>Luther</hi> ſaith, is harder to do, then to raiſe the dead) if bare reading will ſerue the turne. To conclude therefore, let vs acknowledge, that the Word preached and applied to the conſcience, is that ordinance of God, which he hath ſanctified for the conuerſion and ſaluation of men. As the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith: <hi>It pleaſed God by the fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of preaching</hi> (as profane men eſteeme of it) <hi>to ſaue them that beleeue,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21. And yet more plainely, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 14, 15. <hi>How ſhall they call on him, in whom they haue not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued? and how ſhall they beleeue in him, of whom they haue not heard? and how ſhall they heare without a Preacher? And how ſhall they preach, except they be ſent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vſe of this, is firſt for vs that be <hi>Miniſters.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the people. For vs that be <hi>Miniſters:</hi> it ſerueth firſt for the reproofe of two ſorts of
<hi>Miniſters.</hi> Firſt, of ſuch as are altogether vnlearned, and cannot at all performe this dutie; which occupie a roome in the Church, but haue no abilitie at all to teach the people committed to their charge.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſuch as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaketh of, ſaying, There are many
<hi>Prieſts,</hi> and there are few <hi>Prieſts:</hi> many in name, few in deed. They are like that fooliſh <hi>Rhetorician,</hi> which <hi>Tully</hi> makes mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of, that made his ſcholars a great deale more ſottiſh, then when he firſt tooke them: Where they could learne nothing but ignorance of learning. And ſo God knoweth, a number of Gods people, liuing vnder ſuch vnlearned <hi>Miniſters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>are euer learning, and can neuer
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16447:16"/>come to any knowledge of the truth:</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith in another caſe. I would all ſuch Miniſters would regard that which <hi>B. lewel</hi> ſpeaketh to this purpoſe: Whoſoeuer,<note place="margin">In his expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi>
3.7.</note> ſaith he, asketh the pay of a ſouldier, muſt buckle his armour and goe to warfare: he that would drinke the wine, muſt plant the Grape: hee that deſireth the milke, muſt feede the flocke: he that will not be muzled, muſt threſh out the Corne: he that reapeth carnall things, muſt ſow ſpirituall things: he that requireth the bread of the earth, muſt giue the bread of heauen: hee that would liue of the ſacrifice, muſt offer the ſacrifice: hee that would liue of the Altar, muſt waite at the Altar: he that would liue of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, muſt preach the Goſpell. Hee that doth none of all theſe, I can make no account of him, he is not within <hi>Pauls</hi> reckoning. The workeman is worthy of his wages: but what right hath hee to the hire, that is not a worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? Thus farre <hi>Iewel.</hi> And no doubt, that which the
<hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith of bodily labour, is true alſo in this caſe:<note place="margin">2.
<hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.10.18.</note> 
               <hi>He that will not worke, ſhould not eate.</hi> Who would haue a man to bee a <hi>Captaine</hi> in warre, that is not expert in war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare? or to practiſe
<hi>Phiſick</hi> or <hi>Surgerie,</hi> that is not skilfull in that profeſſion? The
<hi>Miniſter</hi> is a <hi>Captaine,</hi> and a guide of Gods people, a <hi>Phiſicion</hi> of their ſoules, and therefore, there is great reaſon that he ſhould be ſufficient.</p>
            <p>But they wil pleade for themſelues, that they are called of the Church, and therfore are not to be diſallowed. As in deed, euen the moſt vnworthy of them all, are alwaies boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of their calling. There is nothing ſo much in their mouthes as that. But I anſwere, that it is moſt true, and may not, nor cannot bee denied, that the calling of the Church is moſt neceſſary for the making of a Miniſter. And though a man were furniſhed with as rare and excellent gifts, and had as great abilitie to preach the Goſpell, as euer had the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> yet hee may not take vpon him the office of a Miniſter, in an ordinary time, and in a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led gouernement of the Church, vnleſſe hee bee lawfully
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16447:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>called by them that haue authoritie in the Church to ordaine
<hi>Miniſters.</hi> Extraordinarie calling of men, ſuch as no doubt <hi>Luther</hi> had,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 13.2, 3.</note> neuer hath place, but where ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie calling wanteth. But yet for all this, the outward calling of the Church alone, is not ſufficient to make a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, vnleſſe he be alſo inwardly called of God. Now the Lord calleth no man to any place, but he furniſheth and fitteth him with gifts, to diſcharge the duties of his place. When he called <hi>Bezaleel</hi> and <hi>Aholiab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lxod.</hi> 31.2, 3,
4.</note> to make garments and inſtruments for the Tabernacle, hee firſt filled them with the
<hi>Spirit of God in wiſedome, and in vnderſtanding, and in knowledge, and in all workemanſhip: To finde out curious workes to worke in gold, and in ſiluer, and in braſſe, &amp;c.</hi> And when <hi>Gedeon</hi> was called from his Trdde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi>
6.3, 4.</note> to be the <hi>Captaine</hi> and deliuerer of the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> it is ſaid, that <hi>the Spirit of the Lord</hi> (euen the Spirit of courage and fortitude) <hi>came vpon him, and clad him</hi> like a garment. So likewiſe when <hi>Saul</hi> was choſen to be King ouer <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.9.</note> 
               <hi>God gane him ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heart:</hi> That is, a ſtout and a valiant heart, fit for a King. If God doe thus furniſh men with gifts neceſſarie, when he calleth them to offices in the Common-wealth: can we doubt of the like care in him, to furniſh them ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently, whom he calleth to ſerue in his Church, in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of his Word?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12.</note> And this the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> PAVL con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth and acknowledgeth of himſelfe, that as the Lord in his mercie <hi>counted him faithfull</hi> (though moſt vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, hauing been before <hi>a blaſphemer, and a perſecuter, &amp;c.) and put him in his ſeruice;</hi> ſo alſo <hi>he made him ſtrong</hi> to the performance of his dutie. As he called him to preach the
<hi>Goſpell,</hi> ſo he gaue him ſtrength and abilitie to doe it with fruite and profit. Hence (as we haue heard before) when the calling and Commiſsion of the <hi>Prophet</hi> Is AIAH was to be renued,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſei.</hi> 6.6, 7.</note> his <hi>lips were touched with a coale from the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 1.5, 9.</note> And when the
<hi>Prophet</hi> IEREMIAH was to be ſent to preach vnto the Nations, the Lord firſt <hi>touched bis mouth, and ſaid, Behold, I haue put my words in thy mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:16447:17"/>And the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 24.49.</note> before they went foorth to the execution of their office, they were firſt <hi>endued with power fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on high.</hi> And howſoeuer all theſe examples be extraordinarie, yet ſtill, whomſoeuer the Lord calleth by ordinarie meanes, hee maketh him in ſome meaſure ſufficient to diſcharge the dutie that appertaineth vnto him. And therefore, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a man haue as well an inward calling from God, as an outward calling from the Church, hee is no true Miniſter, he is but halfe a Miniſter. As the Lord denounceth againſt the <hi>Prieſts</hi> in the time of the Law,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe thou haſtrefuſed knowledge, I will alſo refuſe thee, that thou ſhalt be no Prieſt to me.</hi> They may be Miniſters to ſatisfie Law, but they are no Miniſters of God. As <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith plainely,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> ep. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> They that are vnworthie, are not ordained of God, nor by God. And therefore, by the way, it were to bee wiſhed, that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of the Church, to whom this authoritie to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point <hi>Miniſters</hi> is committed,<note place="margin">De conſid. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> would alwaies in all their ordinations, remember that which
<hi>Bernard</hi> writeth to <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genius:</hi> namely, that they would make it their chiefeſt care to bring in ſuch, as after they haue brought them in, they may not repent of it. But to returne to theſe <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> againe, and to their calling.<note place="margin">Expoſition in 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> IEWEL ſaith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly and plainely, that they that enter into the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, muſt be allowed not of men onely, but of God. And therefore, whoſoeuer taketh that charge ouer the people, muſt looke narrowly into himſelfe, and ſee whether his calling be of God. Vnleſſe he haue a teſtimonie that God hath called him inwardly, all outward calling is to ſmall purpoſe. God is a iuſt Iudge, and will ſay vnto him, <hi>Friend, how cameſt thou in hither, &amp;c.</hi> And indeede what comfort can a man haue in his place, when his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall tell him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 17.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23.21.</note> that <hi>he hath thruſt in himſelfe to bee a Paſtour,</hi> as the <hi>Propbet</hi> ſaith, and that <hi>hee hath runne, when the Lord hath not ſent him?</hi> TINDAL, that bleſſed <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,</hi> doth ſharpely reproue ſuch kinde of <hi>Miniſters.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Expoſit. in
<hi>Matth.</hi> 5.</note> In what caſe are they, ſaith he, that haue benefices, and preach
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16447:18"/>not? verily, though they ſtand at the Altar; yet they are excommunicate, and caſt out of the liuing Church of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God. And againe, Prieſts that preach not, are none of Chriſts, nor none of his anointing: but ſeruants of the beaſt, whoſe marke they beare. And good Father <hi>Latimer</hi> ſaith after his blunt and plaine manner:<note place="margin">In a Sermon preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the ſixth.</note> If there were but one vnpreaching Miniſter, there were too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by one. And againe, as good Preachers are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of double honour, ſo theſe are worthie of double diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour. And what is this double diſhonour, ſaith he, If the ſalt be vnſauory, it is good for nothing, but to caſt out, and to be troden vnder foot of men. By this ſalt, is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood ſuch as haue cure of ſoules. If they be negligent, what be they worthy of? wherefore ſerue they? for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to be caſt out: that is one diſhonor. Another diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, is to be troden vnder foote of men: that is, not to be regarded, not to be eſteemed. And againe, I ſay, if one were admitted to view hell, and to behold it throughly: the Deuill would ſay: On yonder ſide are puniſhed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preaching Miniſters: I thinke a man ſhould ſee as farre as hee could kenne, and ſee nothing but vnpreaching Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. This was the iudgement of theſe worthie men, and reuerend Fathers of our Church: thus they thought of all ſuch <hi>Miniſters,</hi> as occupy a roome in the Miniſtery, and haue no abilitie to doe the dutie of <hi>Miniſters.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are the very calamity and plague of the Church. They keepe the people in ignorance and blindneſſe, to the deſtruction of many a poore ſoule, if God be not mereiful. As the Lord ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hof.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Prou.</hi> 29.18.</note> 
               <hi>My people are deſtroyed for lacke of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> And, <hi>Where there is no viſion,</hi> (that is, where there is no preaching of the doctrine of God out of the Law and the Prophets) <hi>the people decay:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tremel. in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in locum. Serm. on <hi>1.</hi> Pet. <hi>4.11.</hi>
               </note> or as
<hi>Tremellius</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it, <hi>are made naked.</hi> Biſhop <hi>Iewell</hi> vrging the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of preaching, hath a good ſaying, that euen as when the Sunne is taken out of the World, all things are left dorke: ſo is it when the voice of the Paſtor is not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16447:18"/>heard in the Church. And in another place he ſaith,<note place="margin">Serm. on <hi>Luke</hi> 10 23.24.</note> Wher<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the Word is not preached, there the Church muſt needes runne vpon the rocke. Little maruell is it if faith faile, where good inſtruction wanteth.<note place="margin">Vbi ſupra.</note> And <hi>Latimer</hi> goeth yet further: Take away preaching, ſaith hee, and take away ſaluation. GOD helpe thoſe poore Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, that grone vnder the burden of ſuch Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
            <p>I haue no purpoſe to diſgrace any mans perſon. Onely my earneſt deſire is, to perſwade all that haue any gifts, though neuer ſo ſmall, not to ſuffer them to ruſt as they doe for want of vſe. I confeſſe, that it may not bee looked for, that there ſhould bee a like meaſure and proportion of gifts in all Miniſters. For as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11.</note> 
               <hi>The Spirit of God diſtributeth them ſeuerally to euery man as he will.</hi> But as it was ſaid of <hi>Dauids Worthies,</hi> that though diuers of them <hi>did not attaine to the firſt three,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2.
<hi>Sam.</hi> 23.19, 23.</note> 
               <hi>yet they were moſt excellent and honourable among others:</hi> So though wee bee much inferiour to them,<note place="margin">Horat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> whoſe gifts are moſt eminent in the Church, yet let vs ſtriue to bee as excellent as wee can. And therefore, they that haue any meaſure of giftes, let them bee admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed to <hi>ſtirre them vp,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>1.6.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> TI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MOTHEVS: Where hee vſeth a word taken from a ſparke of fre, raked vp vnder the aſhes, which by gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle blowing, is quickened and kindled to a flame. And indeede, there were neuer more helpes to further a man this way, then there are in this age wherein wee liue, if he haue any wit to make vſe of them, or any deſire to doe good with them. It was a very good ſpeech, which our worthy and reuerend Dioceſan in his laſt viſitation at
<hi>Lincolne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">B. Barlow.</note> vſed to ſome vnprofitable Miniſters there preſent, that if they would but diligently ſtudie the <hi>Engliſh</hi> bookes of
<hi>Dininitie</hi> that are now in print, they might doe much good in Gods Church. For haue we not the writings of many excellent Miniſters of our owne
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16447:19"/>Church, as D. <hi>Willet,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Greencham,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Perkins,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Dod,</hi> and others publiſhed for the benefit of all men? And are not the learned workes of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Caluin,</hi> and other Miniſters of forraine Churches, as alſo S.
<hi>Auguſtines</hi> excellent booke of the Citie of God, tranſlated into our owne language? All which if they bee read with diligence, may furniſh a man with competent knowledge of Diuinitie. And haue we not many of our owne Writers that haue trauelled alſo very profitably in handling the controuerſies betweene vs and the <hi>Papiſts?</hi> as B. <hi>Iewel,</hi> D. <hi>Rainold,</hi> D. <hi>Abbot,</hi> D. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let,</hi> D. <hi>Morton,</hi> and others? And if any man deſire to bee inſtructed alſo in matter of hiſtorie, and other humane learning, are not the workes of
<hi>Liuie, Plinie, Plutarch, Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus, Euſebius</hi> and others, turned alſo into
<hi>Engliſh?</hi> Nay, indeede what learning is there almoſt, that a man deſireth to know, but (God make vs thankefull for ſo great a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) he may haue it in his owne mother tongue? So that now, vnleſſe a man will be wanting to himſelfe, though he be neuer ſo much a <hi>Lacke-Latine,</hi> as we vſe to ſay, though he vnderſtand no more tongues, then that hee was borne with, yet he may be able to teach the people committed to his charge, and to inſtruct them profitably, at leaſt, in the grounds and principles of religion. Let them therefore be excited to ſhake off that ſlothfull negligence, that hath ſo long poſſeſſed them: and let them at the laſt ſeriouſly ſet themſelues to the Lords worke, and pray earneſtly for Gods bleſſing; ſo ſhall they become more profitable to the Church, and haue a great deale more comfort in their owne conſciences. But if there be any that haue no gifts, nor abilitie at all to diſcharge their dutie, (as God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, there are many ſhepheards that differ but little from their flocke) I know not what to ſay to them: but as the poore woman ſaid to the Heathen King, that could not attend to doe her iuſtice, <hi>Why then doeſt thou raigne?</hi> ſo I ſay, what doe they in the place of <hi>Miniſters,</hi> if they bee no way able to doe the dutie of <hi>Miniſters?</hi> There is a good
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16447:19"/>Preſident for them in the <hi>Propheſie</hi> of <hi>Zechariah:</hi> where the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeaketh of ſome ſuch <hi>Frieſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.4, 5, 6.</note> that peſtered the Church in his time, that
<hi>they ſhould no longer weare a rough garment to deceiue: But he ſhall ſay, I am no Prophet, I am an Husbandman: for man tanght mee to bee an Heard-man from my youth vp:</hi> That is, he ſhall lay aſide his Prieſtly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite,<note place="margin">Gualter &amp; Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mellius in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum illum.</note> and ſhall freely confeſſe his ignorance, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that he ought rather to be ſent away to the plough, or to play the Shepheard, then to be ſuffered any longer in the Miniſtery of the Church, and ſo ſhall willingly betake himſelfe to the labour of his hand, that hee may no longer bee a burden to the Church. And where it is ſaid in the next verſe, <hi>And one ſhall ſay vnto him, What are theſe wounds in thy hands? Then he ſhall anſwere, Thus was I woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the houſe of my friends.</hi> The meaning of it is, that he will be ſo farre from murmuring and complaining for the loſſe of his gaine and honour, as that rather hee will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them his greateſt friends, that firſt perſwaded him to leaue his ſinne. Oh that our ignorant and inſufficient <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> would follow this example. There are many of them of ſtrong and able bodies, and though they cannot worke this worke of a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> yet no doubt they would prooue tall workemen in other things. It were a happy thing for Gods Church, if they would returne to thoſe profeſsions, wherein they were brought vp and exerciſed, before they entred into the Miniſtery, and wherein they haue more skill. So doing, though their life would be ſomewhat more painefull then now it is, yet doubtleſſe, their ſleepe would be a great deale more ſweete and comfortable. As
<hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>The ſleepe of the labouring man is ſweete, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he eate little or much.</hi> Whereas now I cannot ſee, how they can take any quiet reſt, when their guiltie conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces doe continually barke againſt them, or if they haue gagged their conſciences for a time, yet the bloud of ſo many ſoules, which haue periſhed through their negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16447:20"/>cryeth lowder in the eares of God for vengeance, then cuer did the bloud of
<hi>Habel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 4.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Another ſort of <hi>Miniſters</hi> that come within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of this reproofe, are ſuch as are idle, that though they haue gifts, whereby they might doe much good, yet ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or neuer vſe them. They neuer entred into the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie with any purpoſe to ſerue the Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> but rather <hi>their owne bellies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.18.</note> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith. If they may <hi>eate the fat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 34 3.</note> 
               <hi>and clothe themſelues with the wooll,</hi> they care not greatly what becommeth of the flocke. But they might know, that the calling vnto the Miniſterie is not directed to that ende, that ſuch <hi>ſlow bellies</hi> ſhould onely enioy the dignities, and idly poſſeſſe the reuenues of the Church, but according to the common ſaying,<note place="margin">Beneficium da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur propter offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium.</note> A benefice is giuen for the duties ſake. And this is that which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith:
<hi>The Elders that rule well are worthy of double honour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim</hi>
5.17.</note> 
               <hi>ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De conſid. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>they that labour in the word and doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this purpoſe <hi>Bernard</hi> hath a worthy ſaying: There haue been <hi>Biſhops,</hi> ſaith hee, that would wholly ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the feeding of their ſheepe, glorying in the work and name of a ſhepheard; counting nothing vnbeſeeming them, but that which might be thought to hinder the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of their ſheepe; not ſeeking, but beſtowing their owne things, beſtowing their care, beſtowing their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, beſtowing euen themſelues, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>I will be beſtowed for your ſoules.</hi> All their gaine was for their people; their onely pompe, and their onely pleaſure was to prepare them a perfect people to the Lord. But where Is now this cuſtome? a farre vnlike is come in the place of it. Theſe ſtudies are changed into other, and I feare, into the worſe,<note place="margin">In Declamat.</note> &amp;c. And in another place, he is conuinced to be vnworthy of the milke and the wooll, that doth not feede the ſheepe, that doth not watch for the ſafegard of the flocke. Such a man eateth and feedeth vpon his owne iudgement: Woe, woe be vnto thee: Behold, death is in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16447:20"/>the pot; death is in the fleſh-pots, death is in the delights of this world, and eſpecially for this, becauſe it is manifeſt, that they are the ſinnes of the people which thou eateſt. It were better for thee to digge, yea, to begge. For thou ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the ſins of the people, as if thine owne were not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for thee. Our Sauiour Chriſt, when he called his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, hee bids them follow him, and hee would make them <hi>Fiſhers of men: Matthew</hi> 4.19. Wherevpon one well obſerueth, CHRIST hath not enioyned them, to fiſh for great liuing, and other dignitie, nor for earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gaine, or for the praiſe of men. They that doe ſo, ſhew that they are rather from the Deuill fiſhers of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, then from God fiſhers of men. Let theſe men harken to that which <hi>Biſhop</hi> IEWEL ſaith of ſuch as they are. O what a caſe, ſaith he, are they in,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Expoſit. in</hi> 1.
<hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.17, 18.</note> that are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of Gods people, that hunt after many liuings, and bend themſelues to doe no good: which ſerue their owne belly, and ſeeke to be rich, and eate vp Gods people as it were bread! What account ſhall they giue to God for the ſoules of their brethren? where ſhall they ſtand, or what ſhall they ſay, when they ſhall be called to giue account of their Stewardſhip? It were to be wiſhed, that they that are gouernours of the Church, would vſe their authoritie, to reforme this groſſe idleneſſe of the Miniſters. They might iuſtly ſay to them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.17, 18.</note> as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaid cruelly to the poore
<hi>Iſraelites, Yee are too much idle, get you to your worke, and to your burdens.</hi> Is it not a lamentable thing, that wee ſhould haue ſome that goe for licenſed Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, that preach not once in ſeuen yeeres? If theſe be Preachers, they are Preachers by the contrary. They may bee fitly compared to <hi>Welles without water,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi>
2.17.</note> which a wearie traueller commeth to, in hope to quench his thirſt: but alas, he goeth away diſcomforted:<note place="margin">Iude verſ. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> or to <hi>cloudes without raine,</hi> which giue men ſome hope of a ſhewre, to water and refreſh the earth: but in the ende their hope is fruſtrate. They are like that <hi>Fig-tree</hi> which our
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16447:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>Sauiour curſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 11.13.</note> that flouriſhed with leaues, but had no fruit. So many of them make a very faire ſhew with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward grauitie, but they want inward ſubſtance. In a word, they are like thoſe <hi>Idols</hi> in the <hi>Pſalme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.5. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2.</note> that
<hi>haue mouthes, but they ſpeake not.</hi> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, that <hi>it is required of the Lords Stewards, that they be found faithfull.</hi> But alas, to do nothing at all, to take no paines, but to bury themſelues in idleneſſe, is not to be faithfull; and therefore ſuch Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters can haue no comfortable aſſurance that they are <hi>Gods Stewards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, this ſerueth to exhort vs all that are entred into this high calling, with care and conſcience to ſet our ſelues to preach the Word vnto the people committed to our charge.<note place="margin">Tacit. Annal. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> And that not now and then onely, but with the greateſt diligence we can vſe. For as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith of almes, that <hi>God loueth a cheerefull giuer,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. ſo we ſhould addreſſe our ſelues to the performance of this dutie with all alacritie and chearefulneſſe, counting the buſineſſes of our calling our recreations,<note place="margin">Devita ſolitar.</note> as was ſaid of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> the <hi>Emperour:</hi> and with good <hi>B. Iewell,</hi> thinking it our greateſt honour to die in the Pulpit. And howſoeuer it may ſeeme hard and difficult at the firſt, yet diligence and frequent vſe will make it eaſie. The Husbandman, we ſee, hath hard ſinewes and ſtrong armes. Exerciſe, ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> hath made it ſo, as by ſlouthfulneſſe he becomes effeminate. The will cauſeth vſe, vſe cauſeth exerciſe, and exerciſe miniſtreth ſtrength in all labour. And it was a good ſaying of
<hi>Boetius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſcipl-Schola.</note> that as in euery worke conſtancie and diligence is found to be a mother: ſo on the contrary ſide, of all learning and diſcipline negligence is the ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother. And as the Heathen Orator ſaid,<note place="margin">Cic. pro. C. Rabir.</note> vſe and practice is the beſt maſter. Neither muſt we be diſcouraged, though as many times it falleth out, we ſee little fruit follow our labours.<note place="margin">Plin. ſecund. lib. <hi>6.</hi> ep. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> He that taketh in hand to fell, and cut downe a great Oke, though after many ſtrokes with his axe, it ſeeme to ſtand as ſtrong as euer it did; yet hee giueth not
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16447:21"/>ouer, but redoubleth his ſtroke with greater force, til at the laſt it fall, and then hee ſeeth that his former ſtrokes were not in vaine. A louing Mother, though the froward child do often refuſe the meat, and ſpit it out: yet leaueth not for that, but ſtill feedeth it, and putteth the meate into the mouth againe, and at the laſt it eateth. So though our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple bee hard to worke vpon, and froward to receiue any thing that is good, yet wee muſt not leaue them to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but apply and follow them with inſtruction, and in time they may become more pliable. Neuer any of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi> could conuert all that they taught.<note place="margin">In a Sermon vpon 1. <hi>Pe.</hi> 4.11</note> and B.
<hi>Iewel,</hi> God himſelfe, ſaith hee, husbanded the Vine, and yet it brought forth <hi>wilde grapes, Iſaiah</hi> 5.2.4. God himſelfe <hi>ſtretched out his hands all the day to a rebellious people: Iſa.</hi> 65.2. And Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>would often haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered Ieruſalems children together, as the hen gathereth her chickens vnder her wings, and they would not, Mat.</hi> 23.37. Let vs, ſaith he, doe our endeuour, and leaue the ſucceſſe to the Lord. For this cauſe we are called <hi>Fiſhers, Mat.</hi> 4.19.<note place="margin">Ouid.dearte.</note> Now we know that <hi>Fiſhermen,</hi> whether they fiſh with net or with angle, doe make many a draught, and caſt many a baite into the water, and catch but a little fiſh. <hi>Simon Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and his fellowes had <hi>trauelled a whole night, and caught nothing: Luke</hi> 5.5. yet they were not diſcouraged, but at Chriſts commandement let downe the net againe, and then they incloſed a great multitude of fiſhes. So in like manner, though wee loſe our labour many times; yet we muſt not giue ouer: Chriſt may bring fiſhes into our nets, when we looke not for it. We are compared to <hi>ſeeds-men: Luk.</hi> 8.11. Now all the ſeed which the Sower caſteth into the ground doth not fructifie. Nay, as our Sauiour doth teach vs in that parable, that of foure kinds of grounds, there is but one good ground, which receiueth the ſeede with profit. To which purpoſe,<note place="margin">De Doctr. Chriſt.</note> S.
<hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath a good ſaying, They that heare and learne not, what is it to the ſeedes-man? Nether the high-way, nor the ſtones, nor the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16447:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>thornes doe terrifie the hands of the Seeds-man: he caſteth that which is his: he that ſhall be afraid, leſt his ſeede fal vpon bad ground, doth not come vnto good ground. We are called <hi>Phiſicians</hi> of mens ſoules. But there is no <hi>Phiſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> that cureth all his patients.<note place="margin">De Conſid. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> As
<hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith wittily: Be not diſcouraged, there is care and diligence required of thee, not curing and healing. Thou haſt heard it ſaid in the Goſpell, Take care of him, not cure or heale him. One ſaid ture, It is not in the <hi>Phiſicion</hi> alwaies to relieue the ſick partie. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, I laboured more then they all: he doth not ſay, I profited more then they all. Yea, it may bee, that the labours may doe good, though thou ſeeſt it not. A veſſell that often receiueth water into it, though it be preſently powred out againe: yet it is cleanſed at the laſt, though not at the firſt, nor the ſecond time. In like manner, doe not thou ceaſe to powre water vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the the vncleane, though they be not cleanſed at the firſt powring, yet with often powring they may. As <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> ſaith well to the ſame purpoſe: It is impoſſible that the Word of God ſhould be preached without fruite. But though all bee not conuerted: yet there are ſome, that of ſinners, will become beleeuers, and be ſaued. For the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the Miniſterie is not in the will of men, but of God. As
<hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prou.</hi> 20.12. <hi>The Lord hath made both theſe, euen the eare to heare, and the eye to ſee:</hi> that is to ſay: It is both of the gift of God, that there ſhould be ſome to teach ſound doctrine, and ſome to obey the ſound Teachers. And a little further hee addeth: The good ground will bring foorth fruite, let the other three parts goe to the deuill. But though it ſhould fall out, that no fruite at all ſhould bee ſeene in reſpect of the people:<note place="margin">De Conſid. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> yet wee ſhall bee ſure not to loſe our labour. For as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, Euery man ſhall receiue according to his labour, not according to his ſucceſſe. So, doe thou that, that belongs to thee: For God will ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looke to that, that appertaineth to him, without thy care
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16447:22"/>and thought-taking. Plant, water, take paines, and thou haſt done thy part: doubtleſſe God will giue the increaſe, when hee thinkes good, and not thou. But if he will not, thou loſeſt nothing, as the Scripture ſaith, God will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a reward to the labour of his Saints. It is ſecure labour which no defect can make fruſtrate. And this was the
<hi>Apoſtle Pauls</hi> comfort, that hauing been diligent in the diſcharge of his dutie, and hauing omitted no paines nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther publike nor priuate, whatſoeuer fruite followed of his Miniſtery, hee was <hi>pure from the bloud of all men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi>
20.26.</note> And the Lord telleth the <hi>Prophet</hi> EZECHIEL, that if hee faile not to warne the wicked of the danger of his ſinne, though hee <hi>will not turne from his wicked way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo die in his iniquitie,</hi> yet hee ſhould <hi>deliuer his owne ſoule.</hi> True it is, that it ought to bee the deſire of euery good <hi>Miniſter,</hi> that if it pleaſe God, all his people may be conuerted, and ſo come to ſaluation. But if this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee effected, but that the Lord doe rather by his Miniſterie, make them fagots for hell fire, and though his preaching <hi>bee the ſauour of death vnto death</hi> vnto them all, and not <hi>the ſauour of life</hi> vnto any:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15, 16.</note> yet if hee haue faithfully and conſcionably done that that was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him, he ſhall ſtill be a <hi>ſweet ſauour vnto God.</hi> And herein our condition that are Gods husbandmen, is farre better then the condition of an earthly husbandman. When he hath caſt his ſeede into the ground, if the harueſt doe not anſwere his expectation, hee loſeth not onely his labour, but his ſeede alſo. But if we haue done our duty to the vttermoſt of our power, though for any thing that we can ſee, as the
<hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith, <hi>We haue laboured in vaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi>
49.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>and ſpent our ſtrength in vaine and for nothing: yet our indgement is with the Lord, and our worke with our God.</hi> And though our people <hi>will not be gathered</hi> by our Miniſtery: yet <hi>ſhall we be glorious in the ſight of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, though our people out of a froward diſpoſition, do wrong vs, and offer vs iniurie, yet wee muſt not giue
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16447:23"/>ouer our paines. A mother caſteth not away her childe, though it haue made her breſts ſore with ſucking, but with patience endureth the ſmart, to doe the childe good. So muſt we,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24, 25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.2.</note> (as the
<hi>Apoſtle</hi> commandeth vs) <hi>ſuffer euill men patiently, and inſtruct them with meekeneſſe that are contrary minded, prooning if God at any time will gine them repentance, &amp;c.</hi> Nay, we muſt not be diſcouraged, though our people become our enemies, and perſecute vs. As many times it commeth to paſſe, eſpecially, if we bee ſincere in our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, and doe <hi>plainely rebuke them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leui.</hi>
19.17.</note> 
               <hi>and not ſuffer them to ſin.</hi> Then they rage, and then they vſe al their power to worke vs trouble. As indeede that ſpeech of <hi>Luther</hi> is moſt true. To preach the Word of God ſincerely, is nothing elſe, but to draw vpon a mans ſelfe all the fury of hell and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and all the power of the world. And it is a moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous kind of life, to offer a mans ſelfe to ſo many teeth of Satan. This was the condition of all the
<hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> as may be ſeene in the whole courſe of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And there are but a few faithfull Miniſters at this day, but they haue experience of it. But we muſt not faint for fall this,<note place="margin">De Conſid. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> but rather, as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, if they be of an hard forehead, wee muſt alſo harden ours againſt them. There is nothing ſo hard, that will not yeeld to a harder. And this is that which the Lord ſaid to the <hi>Prophet Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel,</hi> that though the people,<note place="margin">Ezech. 2.6. &amp; 3.8, 9.</note> with whom he had to deale, <hi>were rebels and thornes, and ſcorpions,</hi> yet, ſaith he, <hi>I haue made thy face hard againſt their faces, and thy forehead hard againſt their foreheads. I haue made thy forehead as the Adamant, and harder then the flint: feare them not therefore, neither bee afraid at their lookes.</hi> And the like commandement did the Lord giue to the <hi>Prophet</hi> IEREMIAH,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerem.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>Thou therefore,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>truſſe vp thy loines, and ariſe, and ſpeake vnto them all that I command thee: be not afraide of their faces, leſt I deſtroy thee before them.</hi> Wee may not bee dumbe and cowardly dogs, that dare not barke at mens beards, if they be great and of any power: but we muſt be of generous ſpirits, not
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16447:23"/>fearing the face or big looks of any man. And indeed, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are the ſeruants of God, we need not feare, but that he will protectvs in the diſcharge of our duties. Wee ſee, that great men in the world doe beare out their ſeruants: much more will the Lord beare out his ſeruants, that doe him faithfull ſeruice in the Miniſterie of his Word. As he promiſed the <hi>Prophet</hi> IEREMIAH: <hi>Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 1.18,
19.</note> 
               <hi>I haue made thee this day a defenced Citie, and an iron pillar, and walles of braſſe againſt the whole land, &amp;c. For they ſhall fight againſt thee, but they ſhall not preuaile againſt thee: for I am with thee, to deliuer thee, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vſe of this doctrine for the people, is firſt to reproue them that account the
<hi>Miniſters</hi> life to be an eaſie life. As the moſt of them thinke, that we get our liuing eaſily, we take no paines, but patter on a booke a little, &amp;c. But wee ſee by that that hath been ſpoken, that they are greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. Our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> compareth the work of a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> to things of great labor, as to plowing, fallowing, plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, rearing an houſe, feeding of cattell, and ſuch like, in all which, great paines and diligence is required. <hi>Cato</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">In lib. de agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult.</note> He that tilleth the ground, muſt not ſit ſtill, for he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſomething to doe. And indeede, the worke of the Husbandman is neuer at ende. Sometimes hee fallowes, ſometimes hee ſtirres, ſometimes he carrieth out his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe. Sometimes he ſowes, ſometimes he harrowes, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he weedes: yea euery moneth bringeth with it new worke. So the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> that is Gods husbandman, if hee haue a care to do his dutie well, ſhal find huſineſſe enough to keepe him from being idle. And howſoeuer it be true, that he doe not toyle with his body ſo much as the other doth: yet his labour is much more profitable. The Maſter of the ſhip ſeemeth to be idle; hee ſtirres not the pumpe, he driues not the oares, he rides not the ropes, hee doth no other work that is painefull to the body: and yet his ſtudy and care is more auaileable to the ſafetie of the ſhip, then all their labour. In like manner wee may ſay of faithfull
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16447:24"/>
               <hi>Miniſters,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid of <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and a great deale more truely: They doe not leade an idle life: their eaſe and reſt is more profitable to men, then other mens ſweating and running vp and downe. Nay, if the matter be well conſidered, it will be found, that the continuall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his minde in diligent ſtudy, and the enforcing of his voice in deliuering the word, doth more enfeeble and weaken the bodie, then any other bodily labour. As <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> ſaith well,<note n="(a)" place="margin">In prolog. Declam.</note> The wearineſſe of the wit, is no leſſe then the wearineſſe of the body, but more ſecret. And <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> maketh no bones to ſay, that the labour of the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen hath no proportion to our toyle and ſweat. And whoſoeuer ſhall compare them both together, ſhall eaſily ſee this to be true. The Husbandman that toyleth all the yeere in the field, hath a ſounder complexion, and a better ſtomack, then the poore Miniſter that ſitteth all the day in his ſtudy, and doth nothing, as they thinke, but pore vpon a booke. Let them therefore learne to relinquiſh this er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of theirs, and at the laſt acknowledge, that the life of a conſcionable <hi>Miniſter</hi> is painefull and a laborious life. In deede there are a number of idle Drones that occupy the roomes of <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and they (I confeſſe) liue eaſily e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: for many of them doe little elſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.6.</note> but, <hi>ſit downe to eate and drinke, and riſe vp to play,</hi> as it was ſaid of the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites.</hi> But a godly <hi>Miniſter</hi> that maketh a conſcience of his calling, hath labour and trauell ſufficient, in performing the ſeuerall duties of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it ſerueth for inſtruction. And firſt it teacheth all them that want good
<hi>Miniſters,</hi> what manner of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> they ſhould deſire: namely, ſuch as bee <hi>workemen,</hi> ſuch as be painefull <hi>labourers,</hi> not <hi>loyterers.</hi> As our
<hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.38. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi>
5.17.</note> 
               <hi>Pray the Lord of the Harueſt, that he would ſend forth labourers into his Harueſt,</hi> ſuch as will <hi>labour</hi> diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>in the word and Doctrine.</hi> But alas, the moſt men do little regard this of all other things. If their Miniſter be a quiet man, and will vſe them kindely for their Tithes; if hee be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16447:24"/>a good fellow, and will ſit neighbourly with them, and ſpend his penny, as they doe theirs in the Ale-houſe: if he read them faite ſeruice, as they cal it, and trouble them not with preaching too often: or if he doe ſtep now and then into the Pulpit, if he meddle not too much with their ſins, but <hi>will propheſie vnto them of wine and ſtrong drinke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mich.</hi> 2.11.</note> as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith, and ſo pleaſe their humours, they care for no more, he is the beſt Miniſter for them that can be.</p>
            <p>Againe, for thoſe to whom God in mercie hath giuen faithful Paſtours,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.15.</note> which are carefull to <hi>feede them with knowledge and vnderſtanding:</hi> they muſt learne from hence to be thankefull vnto them. And firſt, they muſt haue them in high eſtimation, and imbrace them with all loue and kinde affection:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17.</note> For they that <hi>labour in the Word and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, are worthie of double honour.</hi> To this purpoſe is that exhortation of the Apoſtle:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ,</hi> 5, 12, 13</note> 
               <hi>Now we beſeech you, brethren, that ye know them which labour among you, &amp;c. That yee haue them in ſingular loue for their workes ſake.</hi> And when he ſent <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> a faithfull Miniſter, and his companion in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to the <hi>Philippians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.25.29.</note> hee bids them
<hi>receiue them in the Lord with allgladneſſe, and make much of ſuch.</hi> And the
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> teſtifieth of the <hi>Galatians,</hi> that they eſteemed ſo reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently of him, as that <hi>they receiued him as an Angell of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.14.
<hi>Eccluſ.</hi> 38, 1.</note> yea, as Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> If we muſt honour the bodily
<hi>Phiſician, becauſe of neceſſitie:</hi> much more muſt we honour the
<hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter,</hi> whom God hath made the <hi>Phifician</hi> of our ſoules. And indeed, the labour of a faithfull <hi>Miniſter</hi> can neuer be ſufficiently recompenced with any dutie or ſeruice which they can performe. For if <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, thought himſelfe to owe more dutie to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his Maſter, that trained him vp in the knowledge of
<hi>Philoſohie,</hi> then to <hi>Philip</hi> his Father that begate him: how much more are men bound to their godly Miniſters, who are not onely their inſtructers to teach them the knowledge of Gods will: but alſo their <hi>ſpirituall Fathers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4
15.</note> 
               <hi>to beget them in Chriſt Ieſus through the Goſpell?</hi> But God knoweth, it fareth with
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16447:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>many of vs,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.15.</note> as it did with the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> that <hi>the more wee loue our people,</hi> and the more wee endeuour to doe them good, <hi>the leſſe we are loued againe.</hi> Let them therefore bee admoniſhed to reforme themſelues herein, and to bee affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with their Paſtours with that loue and kindneſſe that is due vnto them. And the rather, becauſe it will be moſt profitable to themſelues: For if they loue the perſon of the Miniſter, they will a great deale more willingly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace his doctrine, and ſo it will doe them more good. There is nothing more pleaſing to them that are ſicke,<note place="margin">Sanec. lib. <hi>4.</hi> declam.
<hi>5.</hi>
               </note> then to be healed of whom they would.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they muſt be obedient to their doctrin, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> exhorteth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>Obey them that haue the ouerſight of you, and ſubmit your ſelues, &amp;c.</hi> And that for their owne good. For I pray you, what doe the Miniſters gaine by your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience? A comfort, I confeſſe, it is to them, to ſee ſo good fruite of their labours: but all the profit and benefit will be yours in the end. And againe, otherwiſe they are more hardly taught and healed. For as the ſhepheard cannot eaſily cure the ſheepe, that ſpurneth and kicketh with the heeles: and as the patient that ſtruggleth, doth more hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiue a medicine: ſo the ſoule of man cannot bee cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, vnleſſe it doe willingly, and of the owne accord ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it ſelfe vnto diſcipline.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they muſt communicate with them of their goods, and allow them competent maintenance, that ſo without worldly diſtractions, they may more chearefully attend their ſtudies. And there is great reaſon for this of all other duties.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 10.7.</note> For as our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>The labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer is worthie of his wages.</hi> And this is part of that <hi>double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, is due to the Miniſter; and therefore he applieth that precept of the law to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17, 18. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not mouzell the mouth of the oxe that treadeth out the corne.</hi> And, <hi>the Lord hath ordained, that they that preach the Goſpell, ſhould liue of the Goſpell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi>
6.6.</note> And therefore the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> giueth commandement to <hi>all that are taught in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16447:25"/>the Word, that they make him that hath taught them, partaker of all their goods.</hi> And in another place he ſaith, There is no proportion betweene the maintenance which the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> receiue of the people, and that which they afford them backe againe.
<hi>If we,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.11.</note> 
               <hi>haue ſowne vnto you ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things, is it a great matter if we reape your carnall things?</hi> But our people are ſo farre from giuing vs main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of themſelues, as that they vſe all meanes they can, to with-hold that maintenance from vs which the Law hath appointed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi>
18.12.</note> That proud <hi>Phariſee</hi> made his boaſt, and it may bee truely, that <hi>hee gaue tithes of all that euer hee poſſeſſed.</hi> But our people in many places defraude vs by one deuice or other. Eyther they haue ſome Popiſh cuſtome to cut off our Tithes in kinde, or they haue out-grounds in other Pariſhes, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand other trickes, whereby they can defeat vs at their pleaſure. As it is ſtrange to ſee, how ingenious &amp; witty the diuel hath made euen the ſimpleſt of them to beguile their <hi>Miniſter.</hi> But let them take heed that their crafty wit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile not themſelues in the end. Let them beware, that the <hi>cry of the Lords labourers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe hire they haue kept back by fraud, do not enter into the eares of the Lord of hoſts.</hi> We ſhould know, that Gods miniſters ought to be maintained, though the Law had appointed them no tithes at al for their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. And we ſee that the moſt vnworthie Miniſters that are, will haue their tithes to the vttermoſt: yea with greater rigour then they that toile and take moſt paines for them. And therefore, let all the people of God be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted conſcionably, to giue the portion that is due to their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> leſt they bee driuen for want thereof to forſake the houſe of God, as they did in the time of <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, chap.</hi> 13. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10, 11. and as they doe at this day in many places of the land. In a word, let them be carefull to performe this and all other their duties, with ſuch alacrity and chearefulneſſe, as that their
<hi>Miniſters</hi> may be incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to doe their duties backe againe <hi>with ioy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>and not with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16447:26"/>griefe,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith: For doubtleſſe the griefe which a <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhall conceiue from the way-ward and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe diſpoſition of his people, cannot chuſe but greatly daunt his ſpirits, and make him altogether liſtleſſe to preach vnto them. And indeed what heart can a man haue to take paines with ſuch a people, as neither regard him nor his Miniſtery, if that neceſſitie which God hath laid vpon him,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16.</note> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, did not compell him?</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, it may ſerue to admoniſh all true Chriſtians to mourne in their ſoules, and with bitterneſſe of heart to bewaile the miſerie of ſo many thouſands of their poore brethren, who are like to periſh in many places, becauſe there is none to teach them knowledge.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.6.</note> Is it not a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table thing, to ſee ſo many townes for want of preaching <hi>Miniſters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi>
9.2.</note> (who are the <hi>Candleſticks</hi> to hold foorth the light of the Word vnto them)
<hi>ſitting in darkneſſe, and in the ſhaddow of death?</hi> Our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt,</hi> when he ſaw the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.36.</note> that <hi>they were diſperſed and ſcattered abroad, as ſheepe hauing no ſhepheard, his very bowels were moued with compaſſion towards them.</hi> And if we be led by the Spirit of Chriſt, we cannot but be affected with commiſeration, in regard of the like miſerie of the people of our times, that haue no guides, but <hi>blind guides,</hi> to leade them into the ditch.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.14.</note> Would it not grieue any mans heart in the world to ſee a goodly harueſt of croppe, like to rot vpon the earth for want of Reapers to gather it into the barnes?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.37. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.35.</note> Euen ſo, the Lord hath a great harueſt, and the <hi>regions are white</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith: What a griefe then ought it to bee to euery good heart, to conſider, that there are ſo few la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers to thruſt in the Sickle? The people of God in many places, begin to feele the want of the Word, and <hi>as new-borne babes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>they deſire the ſincere milk of it, that they may grow by it.</hi> But alas, what a pittifull thing is it, that their Miniſters are either drie nurſes, and haue no milke at all in their breſts, to giue them ſucke:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.3, 4.</note> or if they haue, they are become through idleneſſe more hard-hearted <hi>then the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16447:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>Dragons,</hi> and more cruell <hi>then the Oſtriches in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: they will not draw out their breſts to feede them,</hi> but euen ſuffer
<hi>the tongue of Gods poore ſucklings to cleaue to the roofe of their mouth for thirſt.</hi> And therefore, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this point, let euery one of vs bee ſtirred vp in a fellow-feeling of this great miſerie, to pray to God in the behalfe of our brethren, and euen to importune him, and giue him no reſt, vntill hee bee pleaſed to ſet ouer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie Congregation ſuch a Miniſter, as may bee apt and able to teach and inſtruct them in the way of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That needeth not to bee aſhamed.</hi>] The word proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignifieth, that needeth not to bluſh.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ab <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21.
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And ſo the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle vſeth it an another place, where hee ſaith,
<hi>What fruite had yee then in thoſe things, whereof ye are now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed?</hi> Heere then hee exhorteth TIMOTHEVS to keepe a good conſcience in the whole courſe of his life, that when hee ſhall come to giue account vnto God, his face may not becouered with ſhame: for where ſhame is, there is guiltineſſe. And thus doth Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> expound it: Liue ſo, ſaith hee, leſt thy wordes wanting deedes, bee confounded: for the doctrine, is an ornament to the life, and the worke is an oſtabliſhment to the life, and the worke is an eſtabliſhment of the doctrine. And <hi>Aquinas,</hi> The doctrine, ſaith hee, which he preacheth with his mouth, let him confirme with his work, which if he do not, he is worthy of ſhame and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And
<hi>Gorra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> interpreteth it, one that needeth not bluſh to conſeſſe the Goſpel for his euil life. <hi>Anſelmus</hi> readeth it vnreproueable. For, ſaith he, from a reproof riſeth confuſion to him that is reproued, and he that cannot be reproued, is not confounded. As if he ſhould ſay, Shew thy ſelfe ſuch a one in al thy works, as in none of them thou maiſt ſuſtaine the confuſion of ſhame. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our inſtruction may be this, That it is not enough for a <hi>miniſter</hi> to preach ſound doctrine, vnleſſe he be blameleſſe in his life. And therefore
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16447:27"/>our <hi>Sauior Chriſt</hi> in that excellent prayer of his for his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, becauſe they were to bee <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Word, prayeth for them to his Father;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.17.</note> 
               <hi>Sanctifie them with thy truth, thy Word is the truth.</hi> And indeede how can they cleanſe others, that are vncleane themſelues? how can they free others from pollution, that are polluted themſelues? according to that ſaying of
<hi>Cyprian:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1 2.</note> who can giue that which himſelfe hath not? And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> exhorteth <hi>Timotheus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1.
<hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.</note> to <hi>take heede to himſelfe, and to doctrine.</hi> Attend firſt to thy ſelfe, and then to the teaching of other: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the ordinary Gloſſe ſaith, He doth not ſay, Attend to doctrine and to thy ſelf: but, Attend to thy ſelfe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to doctrine: firſt, take heed how thou liueſt, and then how thou teacheſt: for as <hi>Caluin</hi> well noteth, doctrine will doe little good, if holineſſe of life bee not anſwerable. And great reaſon is there that <hi>Miniſters</hi> of all other men ſhould bee holy. For firſt, they adminiſter the holy things of God:<note place="margin">Alex. ab Alex. genial. dier.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>4</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> as the
<hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, they are <hi>diſpoſers of the ſecrets of God. They beare the veſſels of the Lord,</hi> as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith, and that after a more peculiar manner: and therefore it behooueth them eſpecially to bee cleane, <hi>Iſay</hi> 52.11. And this the poore Heathen people, in their blind and ſuperſtitious ſeruice of their Idols, had a very great care of.<note place="margin">Sabellicus En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nead. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> It was one of their <hi>Pontificall</hi> lawes: <hi>Det them come chaſtly to the gods, let them vſe pietie. They that do otherwiſe, God himſelfe will reuenge it.</hi> The <hi>Prieſts</hi> of
<hi>Egypt,</hi> euery third day did ſhaue their bodies, leſt any filthineſſe appeare,<note place="margin">Plutarch. in Quaeſt. Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riat. Roman.</note> when they were offering their ſacrifices. And thoſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> that were troubled with Byles and Botches, were forbidden to ſtudy Diuination: either becauſe it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not them to haue any vlcer in their mindes, that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelues to heauenly things: or elſe if they vſe not a diſeaſed beaſt for ſacrifice, nor diſeaſed birds for Diuina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: much more muſt they auoid ſuch things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. If theſe Heathen men had this care for the ſeruice of their falſe gods, which were but ſtockes and ſtones, the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16447:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>workes of their owne hands: how much more ought wee to be carefull of all puritie and cleanneſſe in the worſhip of the true God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi>
12.29. <hi>Leu.</hi> 10.3.</note> who is a <hi>conſuming fire</hi> againſt ſinne and ſinners, and who will <hi>be ſanctified in them that come neere him,</hi> or elſe he will glorifie himſelfe in their confuſion. It was forbidden in the Law,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leu.</hi> 21.17, 18, 19, 20, 21.</note> that <hi>whoſoener had any blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, ſhould not preaſe to offer the bread of his God:</hi> as if hee were <hi>blind, or lame, or had a flat noſe, or any miſſhapen member, &amp;c.</hi> And howſoeuer this ceremonie be ceaſed, and be no more in vſe: yet the equitie of it remaineth ſtill, namely, that they that haue blemiſhes in their liues, or are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhapen in their ſoules, ſhould not be admitted to ſerue the Lord, in the miniſterie of his Word.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a <hi>Miniſter</hi> muſt goe before his people in the example of a godly life. It was the exhortation of our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> to his Diſciples:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good workes, and glorifie your Father which is in heauen.</hi> As in the Orbes and Circles of the Heauens, the higheſt Spheare moueth all the reſt; and therefore is called the firſt Moouer: So the <hi>Miniſter</hi> being higheſt in the Church, ſhould by his example moue and draw them that are vnder him vnto holineſſe. For the people in our times will ſay to vs, as they ſaid to our <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, What doeſt thou worke, that we may ſee it, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue thee?</hi> Not what doeſt thou teach? <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.30. And therefore as it is ſaid of him, that firſt <hi>he began to doe, and then to teach, Act.</hi> 1.1. that he was firſt
<hi>mightie in deed, and then in word,</hi> according as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Serm. <hi>5.</hi> de lapſis. Luke <hi>24.19.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt was a Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher in words, and a performer in deeds; teaching what ought to be done, and doing whatſoeuer he taught. And it is ſaid of <hi>Ezra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra.</hi> 7.10.</note> that firſt
<hi>he prepared his head to ſeeke the Law of the Lord, and to doe it,</hi> and then <hi>to teach the precepts and iudgements in Iſrael.</hi> So muſt it bee with vs, that wee may ſay with the
<hi>Apoſtle</hi> PAVL:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>Brethren, be followers of me, and looke on them that walke, ſo as ye haue vs for an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> And, <hi>Thinke of thoſe things which ye haue both learned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">&amp; 4, 8, 9.</note>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:16447:28"/>
               <hi>and receiued,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>and heard, and ſeent in me.</hi> And to this purpoſe the Apoſtle exhorteth TIMOTHEVS, <hi>to be vnto them that beleeue an enſample, in word, in conuerſation, in loue, in ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>in faith, and in pureneſſe.</hi> And hee biddeth TITVS, <hi>aboue all things to ſhew himſelfe an example of good works, &amp;c.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth all <hi>miniſters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi>
5.3.</note> ſo to carry themſelues, as they may bee <hi>enſamples to the flocks.</hi> In all which places,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the word that is vſed, doth ſignifie, that the life of a <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhould be ſuch a patterne of godlineſſe, as that it may ſet a ſtampe, and an impreſſion thereof, as it were vpon his people. Men wil ſooner learne of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters by their eyes, then they will doe by their eares. For they commonly beleeue their eyes,<note place="margin">Seneca epiſt <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> better then they doe their eares. And it is a long courſe to teach by precepts, but ſhort and effectuall by examples. When the people of Iſrael were to paſſe ouer <hi>Iorden</hi> into the land of promiſe, the <hi>Priests that bare the Arke of the Coxenant,</hi> went before them:
<hi>Ioſh.</hi> 3.15, 16, 17. So muſt the <hi>Miniſters</hi> goe before their people in the iourney to the Kingdome of heauen. And indeede,<note place="margin">Doctr. Chr. lib.
<hi>4.</hi>
               </note> as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, though they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit many by ſaying that which they doe not: yet they would profit a great many more by doing that which they ſay. It is ſaid of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> that <hi>he was the voice of him that crieth in the wilderneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iobn <hi>1 23.</hi> Dominica <hi>3.</hi> aduentus.</note> Whereupon <hi>Stapleton</hi> well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth, that he had not onely a well-ſounding voice, but alſo he was a voice. Whatſoeuer was in him, namely, his food, his apparrell, his habitation, and his whole life, was a voice that cried and proclaimed repentance, mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and holineſſe. His life firſt cried, before his preaching. The ſame order ſhould a Preacher obſerue, that firſt he be a voice, and then lift vp his voice. They whoſe liues are not anſwerable to their doctrine, haue a voice indeed, but an emptie one, like <hi>ſounding braſſe, or a tinckling Cymball,</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Plutarch. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheg. vulgar. Lcc. num.</note> 
               <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1. but they are not a voice, or at leaſt, a man may ſay of them, as the Country fellow ſaid of the Nightin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale, when hee had ſtripped her out of her feathers, Thou
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16447:28"/>art onely a voice, and nothing elſe. This was it that made <hi>Herod</hi> reuerence <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> ſo much,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marke</hi> 6, 20.</note> and heare him ſo gladly, not that he was a good Preacher: but chiefly that he was <hi>a iuſt man, and an holy.</hi> The <hi>Heathen Philoſophers</hi> haue made three markes of a good Teacher: firſt, that he teach not ſleightly and negligently, but diligently, and with due premeditation. Secondly, that he obſerue a good order and methode in teaching, that his hearers may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand him. And laſtly, that his life be anſwerable to his words and profeſsion. Whereunto agreeth that ſaying of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Confeſſ lib.
<hi>10.</hi>
               </note> It is to little purpoſe for a Miniſter to command his hearers in words, if he doe not alſo goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them in deeds.<note place="margin">De Conſid. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> And therefore <hi>Bernard</hi> willeth <hi>Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> to conſider, that it behooueth him to bee a forme of righteouſneſſe, a mirrour of holineſſe, and a patterne of pietie. So ſhould it be with all the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Word,<note place="margin">Cyp. lib.
<hi>3.</hi> epiſt. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that they may exhort their people not by words only, but by deeds, not onely by the incitement of their ſpeech and voice, but chiefly bee the example of their faith and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. And indeed if it be expedient for all men to liue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly,<note place="margin">Cyr. lib <hi>1.</hi> epi. <hi>11</hi>
               </note> much more doth it ſtand with reaſon, that <hi>Miniſters</hi> be carefull that way, whoſe manners and conuerſation ſhould be a leſſon and an example vnto others. For how can they ſee integritie and continency kept, if corruption, and inſtruction of vice begin to proceede from themſelues? And therefore, to ſhut vp all in a word,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> epiſt. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> as
<hi>Cyprian</hi> well counſelleth, let euery <hi>Miniſter</hi> labour to fulfill in deed, that which before he hath taught in word, that ſo he may be the greateſt in the Kingdome of heauen, as Chriſt hath promiſed, ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5 19.</note>
               <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall obſerue and teach theſe words, the ſame ſhall be called great in the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This doctrine hath a double vſe: firſt, for the <hi>Miniſters:</hi> ſecondly, for the people. For the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> it ſerueth firſt to reproue allthoſe that are careleſſe this way, who as our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Phariſes, Say, and doe not:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16447:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>Matth.</hi> 23.3. As God knoweth, there are ſo many ſuch in theſe daies, that we may well vſe that ſpeech of <hi>Bernard; Chriſt</hi> ſaid of his Diſciples:<note place="margin">Declamat.</note> 
               <hi>Haue not I choſen you twelue, and one of you is a Diuell?</hi> But I would there were at this day among twelue <hi>one Peter.</hi> And it is true of a number that <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Cur. Paſtoral.</note> that which they pierce into by their vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, they tread vnder their feete by their liuing: they teach on the ſudden, that which they haue learned, not by practice, but by meditation; and that which they preach in words, they impugne with their manners. Theſe are they that lay heauy burdens on other mens backes, but <hi>themſelues will not moone them with one of their fingers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.4.</note> With what force can they reprooue that in others, which they practiſe themſelues?<note place="margin">Cic prolege Manil.</note> The Heathen man could ſay, that hee cannot be ſeuere in iudging others, that would not haue others ſeuere Iudges againſt himſelfe. And, he that taketh vpon him to correct other mens manners, and to reproue their ſinnes, who will beare with him, if he decline neuer ſo little from the care and conſcience of his dutie?<note place="margin">Idem in Verem. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> And in the ſame place, he is not to be ſuffered, that is taken him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the ſame fault, which he reprooueth in another. The ſnuffers in the Tabernacle,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi>
37.23.</note> which were to top the Lampes, and to make them burne brighter, by Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement were of pure gold, to teach vs, that they that by reprehenſion, muſt cauſe others to giue more light, muſt be pure and cleane themſelues. Otherwiſe, they are like water in the Font, which waſheth others, and it ſelfe deſcendeth into the ſincke: or like a file, that ſmootheth other things, and it ſelfe remaineth rough: or like <hi>Noahs</hi> Carpenters, who made an Arke to ſaue others from drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and themſelues periſhed in the waters. Or like impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent beggars by the High-way ſide, who can well informe trauellers in the way, and yet neuer walke it themſelues: or like him that carrieth a candle behind him, to giue light to them that come after, but himſelfe falleth into the mire: or like a lame man, who ſo long as hee ſitteth ſtill, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16447:29"/>to bee comely and well-fauoured: but aſſoone as hee beginneth to walke, he appeareth deformed. So theſe Miniſters (as is commonly ſaid in diſgrace of them) ſo long as they are in the Pulpit, are good men: but when they come downe, they are moſt wicked:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.5.6.7.</note> or they are like <hi>Dauids</hi> idols, in this reſpect alſo. They haue all the inſtruments of vertue, but they vſe them not. They haue eyes to ſee that which is good, but they follow the worſe: they haue the feete of their affections, but they are not mooued to good: they haue mouthes, but ſuch as haue no taſte of godlineſſe. In a word, they haue IACOBS <hi>voice, and</hi> ESAVS <hi>hands:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 27.22.</note> how can the poore people haue any hope their prayers ſhall be heard, when ſuch prophane perſons as theſe, are their mouth to God? eſpecially ſeeing our Sauiour hath ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.31.</note> that <hi>God heareth not ſinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, their example doth wonderfull much hurt to their people: <hi>If the trumpet giue an vncertaine ſound,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.8. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58.1.</note>
               <hi>who ſhal prepare himſelfe to the battell,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith? The voice of a Miniſter is a trumpet, and it giueth an vncertaine ſound, when it is not confirmed by the teſtimony of his vertues. In ſuch a caſe no man will prepare himſelfe, but rather euery one will laugh him to ſcoine, ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>Thou that teacheſt another, teacheſt not thyſelfe? &amp;c.</hi> If hee that is appointed to bee a guide in the way, ſhall tell the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueller, that he muſt goe one way, and himſelfe goe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way. The poore traueller, knowing him to be skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the right way, will rather follow his ſteppes, then his words. In like manner, the Miniſter that is ſet to bee a guide in the way to heauen, if hee ſhall tell men the right way, but himſelfe walke the way to hell: If hee ſhall bid them goe by the way of mercie, but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe goe by the way of crueltie; if hee bid them goe by the way of temperance, but himſelfe goe the way of drunkenneſſe; if hee bid them goe the way of chaſtitie, but himſelfe goe the way of vncleannes and whoredome,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16447:30"/>it muſt needs be a great ſtumbling blocke vnto the poore people. That which
<hi>Seneca,</hi> though an Heathen man, ſpake of the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> of his time, may fitly be applied to many Miniſters of theſe daies.<note place="margin">Epiſt.
<hi>108.</hi>
               </note> I iudge none, ſaith hee, to deſerue worſe of all mankind, then they that haue learned <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> as a certaine art ſet to ſale, that liue otherwiſe, then they teach others to liue. They ſet foorth themſelues as examples of vnprofitable learning, being ſubiect to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vice, which they inueigh againſt in others. Such a Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher can no more benefit me, then the Pilot that is readie to vomit in a tempeſt.<note place="margin">Epiſt.
<hi>123.</hi>
               </note> And in another place; The ſicke partie hath no hope of health, whom the Phiſician moueth to intemperance. Theſe men, looke how much they build with their doctrine, ſo much they pull downe with their ill life; if ſo be he can build any thing that liueth ill: for as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">De Doct. Chr. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> There are a number, that ſeeke for a defence of their cuill life, euen from their Teachers themſelues, anſwering in their heart, or it may bee, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out into ſpeech, and ſaying, That which thou biddeſt me doe, why doeſt thou it not thy ſelfe? And ſo it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe, that they doe not heare him obediently, that heareth not himſelfe: and the Word of God that is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto them, they contemne together with the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. Thus by their faults,<note place="margin">Cypr. l. <hi>1.</hi> cp. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> they make an example of ruine and downefall to other. As the Prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth of the falſe prophets, that by their ſinfull and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy courſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.14, 15.</note> they did
<hi>ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked, that none could returne from his wickedneſſe.</hi> Nay, from them <hi>wickedneſſe went forth into all the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maſter Green ham.</note> Hence is it, that one calleth ill Miniſters the deuils hawks, and his beſt factors; becauſe there is none that doth more build vp his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom then they. As God knoweth, we ſee for the moſt part, that ſuch Pariſhes as are peſtered with them, are little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the ſuburbes of hell. For alas, is there any thing to be found (except it be in ſome two or three, in whoſe hearts the Lord hath wrought a hungring and thirſting
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16447:30"/>after the Word) but horrible ſwearing and blaſphemy, beaſtly ſwilling and drinking (the Miniſter being not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med nor afraid, to make both himſelfe and others drunke,<note place="margin">Ser n. de chrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</note> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith) filthy vncleanneſſe and whoredom, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious prophanation of the Sabbath, &amp;c? So that though the prouerbe ſeldome hold in the better part, yet it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies true in the worſe part (the force of our corruptions ſwaying vs that way) <hi>Like Prieſt, like people.</hi> So true is that ſaying of Saint <hi>Cyprian:</hi>
               <note place="margin">lib.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. p. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> The ruine of the ouerſeer, is moſt pernicious to the downefall of them that follow him.</p>
            <p>Againe, ſuch Miniſters doe exceedingly hurt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and weaken the credlt of their miniſterie, and make euen the doctrine which they teach to be ſuſpected. Saint
<hi>Auguſtine</hi> maketh it the firſt degree of abuſes,<note place="margin">De decem abuſ. gradib.</note> when a Preacher is without good workes, neglecting that in his actions, which hee teacheth in his ſpeech. For the hearers doe eaſily contemne the ſayings, when they ſee the workes of the Preacher differ from the words of his preaching. For the authoritie of a Preacher is neuer made effectuall, vnleſſe by the practice of his worke, hee faſten it in the heart of his hearers. And in another place he ſaith,<note place="margin">De doctr. Chriſt. lib.
<hi>4.</hi>
               </note> The life of the Teacher is of greater force to make the people heare him obediently, then the greateſt waight of words: whereunto agreeth that ſpeech of
<hi>Gregorie:</hi> His doctrine is contemned, whoſe life is deſpiſed. And no maruell if the people giue no credit to ſuch a mans preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe it is like a writing without a ſeale. And as in ciuill iudgement, the teſtimony of one man is not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but <hi>in the mouth of two or three witneſſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.16.</note> 
               <hi>euery word must be confirmed:</hi> ſo in preaching, men doe not beleeue the voice of the Preacher onely, vnleſſe it be further confirmed by the teſtimony of his life. As <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſaith; The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of teaching is loſt, when the voice is not helped by the worke. A Miniſter by teaching well, and liuing well, inſtructeth the people how to liue: but by teaching well,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16447:31"/>and liuing ill, he inſtructeth God how to condemne him. Nay, he condemneth himſelfe by his owne voice; as it is ſaid in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 19.22.</note> 
               <hi>Of thine owne mouth will I indge thee, thou euill ſaruant.</hi> Such a man carrieth a candle before himſelfe to ſhew others his filthineſſe. He maketh his light to ſhine before men, that they may ſee his euill workes, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe both him and his doctrine.<note place="margin">De conſider. lib.
<hi>2</hi>
               </note> It is a monſtrous thing, ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> for a man to haue the higheſt ſeat, and the loweſt life, loftie words, and idle hands, much ſpeech, and no fruite. Let euery one of vs therefore take heede, that our ill life confute not our good preaching. Happy is hee, who if his doctrine be refuſed, can yet ſay in ſome meaſure with our Sauiour Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iobn</hi> 5.36. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.38.</note> 
               <hi>The workes that I doe, beare witnes of me, that the Father bath ſent me.</hi> And againe: <hi>Though yee beleene not me, yet beleeue my workes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, the ſinnes of a Miniſter are more grieuous, then the ſinnes of other men. The waights of the Sanctuarie were double as heauie as the ordinarie waights of Marchants: ſignifying, that the ſinnes of Miniſters ſhould bee waighed with heauier waights, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue heauier iudgements, then the ſinnes of ordinarie perſons.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 4.3. 12.13 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> And therefore in the Law, there was as great a Sacrifice appointed to bee offered, for the expiation of the ſinne of the Prieſt, as of all the people. And not without iuſt cauſe: For a Miniſter hath, or ſhould haue more knowledge then the people haue. Now where there is more knowledge, there the tranſgreſſour is lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to greater blame. As our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Vnto whomſoener much is giuen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.48.</note> 
               <hi>of him ſhall bee much required.</hi> And beſides, the excellencie of his place is greater. And therefore,<note place="margin">Bern. de conſid. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> if his conuerſation bee lewde and wicked, the more excellent hee is, the more deformed hee ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the ſight of all men. As a little ſtaine of incke is more ſeene in faire white paper, then a great one in browne paper: ſo a ſmall fault in a Miniſter is more notorious, then a great one in another man. The
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16447:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſinne of a Miniſter is like the leproſie of <hi>Vzziah,</hi> that roſe vp in his fore-head, and was in euerie bodies ſight, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.19. but the ſinne of another man is like the leproſie of <hi>Moſes</hi> in his hand, which hee put in his boſome, and ſo kept it from being ſeene, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.6. Not that other mens ſinnes alſo are not ſeene, but becauſe they are not ſo much obſerued, as the ſinnes of the Miniſter.</p>
            <p>A ſecond vſe of this doctrine to vs that be Miniſters, is to excite and ſtirre vs vp to endeuour, that there may bee an agreement betweene our hearts, our mouthes, and our hands,<note place="margin">Tract. <hi>2.</hi> de ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit. Virg.</note> that as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaid of Virgins, when men ſnal ſee our conuerſation, they neede not doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we bee Miniſters or no. And herein wee ſhould la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to imitate God himſelfe, whoſe ſeruants wee are, of whom
<hi>Salomon</hi> ſaich, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 8.24. that whatſoeuer <hi>hee ſpake with his mouth, hee performed it with his hand.</hi> It is an excellent thing, when men ſhall truly ſay of a Miniſter,<note place="margin">Seneca, epiſt. <hi>75.</hi>
               </note> that hee liueth as hee preacheth. And this did the Heathen man require of the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> of his time, that their ſpeech might agree with their life: for he, ſaith hee, hath fulfilled his promiſe, who is the ſame man, both when men ſee him, and when they heare him. As they that are teachers of Muſicke, doe not onely giue certaine precepts to their ſcholars, but alſo ſhew them the practice of it by playing before them themſelues: ſo the Miniſter ſhould not onely deliuer wholeſome doctrine to his people, but alſo ſhew them the practice of it in his owne example. And indeede, as <hi>Hierome</hi> writeth, The houſe and conuerſation of a Miniſter,<note place="margin">Ad Heliodor. cpiſt. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> being ſet as it were on a watch-Tower, ought to bee the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtreſſe of publike diſcipline. Whatſoeuer hee ſhall doe, all his people will thinke they may doe the like. And therefore, they muſt take heed hee giue no cauſe, that either they that will reproue him may ſeeme to raile vpon him worthily, or they that would imitate him,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16447:32"/>may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to offend. And in another place. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of a
<hi>Biſhop</hi> ought to be ſuch, as he may conceiue the truth in his heart, and ſound it forth in his whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, that whatſoeuer hee ſpeaketh, whatſoeuer hee doth,<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> may bee the inſtruction of his people. And
<hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith very wittily of Philoſophy, which is much more true of Diuinitie, that it teacheth men to do &amp; not to ſay, and requireth this of euery man, that he liue after his own Law, that the life diſſent not from the ſpeech: but that the life in it ſelfe be all of one colour, without any diſagreement of all the actions. Such were the ancient Fathers which in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times flouriſhed in the Church. As it is reported of <hi>Origen,</hi> that he had not only perfect Doctrine in his words, but alſo in his workes he ſhewed examples of perfect diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,<note place="margin">Euſeb. Eccl. hiſt. l. <hi>6.</hi>c.<hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and it was ſaid of him, This is he, that hath his life anſwerable to his word, becauſe hee doth thoſe things which he teacheth.<note place="margin">Euſeb. l <hi>11.</hi> ca. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> And it is teſtified of <hi>Gregorie Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen,</hi> that he profited much to the reformation of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, becauſe being a teacher of Religion, hee taught them many things by his words, but farre more by example: neither did they ſee, that he commanded his Diſciples any thing, which he did not firſt himſelfe. And <hi>Eraſmus</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> that his heart burned with Euangelicall pietie, and his ſpeech was anſwerable to his heart: he ſpake eloquent things, and yet rather ſtout and conſtant, then eloquent. Neither did hee onely ſpeake, but liue ſo. So ſhould it bee with all the Miniſters of the Word of God.<note place="margin">Hiſtor. tripartit. l. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> And therefore the <hi>Emperour <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentinian</hi> writing to the <hi>Biſhops</hi> about the election of a new <hi>Biſhop</hi> of
<hi>Millaine,</hi> ſaith in this manner: You know plainely, being taught out of Gods Word, what a manner of man a <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſhould be, namely, that he ought not by word onely to gouerne his people, but by his life alſo; and to ſhew himſelfe a follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of all vertue, and to haue his good conuerſation a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his doctrine.<note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in Ver. li. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> Wherunto agreeth that ſaying of the heathen Orator, that they lay vpon themſelues a Law of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16447:32"/>innocency, continencie, and all vertues, that call others to account for their life. And queſtionleſſe the neglect of this dutie is one maine and principall cauſe why the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of a number ſucceedeth no better. For while they ſpeake out of their reading, and out of their iudgement, and haue no more care to practiſe that which they teach, the people are rather offended, and turned out of the way of godlineſſe, then any whit prouoked to walke in it. And hence it commeth to paſſe many times, that a man of no mouth,<note place="margin">Exod.
<hi>4.10.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Moſes</hi> calleth himſelf, that is, of very meane gifts, that leadeth a godly life, deth more good in Gods Church, then many a prophane man with greater learning. Which is not ſpoken to derogate any thing at all from the moſt neceſſarie helpes of learning, where with a Miniſter ſhould be furniſhed: but rather to ſtirre vs all vp, as we haue been taught, to expreſſe in our liues, that we profeſſe and teach with our mouthes. So would it come to paſſe, that as wee ſhould doe more good to others, ſo we ſhould make our Miniſtery more comfortable to our ſelues. Yea, as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.</note> in the place before alleaged; <hi>We ſhall ſaue our ſelues, and them that heare vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vſe of this doctrine to the people, is to admoniſh them, not to bee offended, though ſometimes they ſee a Miniſter not liue as he teacheth. It is ſtrange to ſee how curiouſly many men with gazing eyes doe prie into the liues and conuerſations of Miniſters, and if they find any thing neuer ſo little amiſſe, they ſtretch it on the tenter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hookes, and make a mountaine of euery mole-hill: crying out with open mouthes againſt the ill liues of all Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, though their owne be a great deale worſe. But hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites as they are, a man may well ſay vnto them, as our Sauiour Chriſt ſaid of ſuch like in his time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.3.</note> 
               <hi>Why ſeeſt thou the mote that is in thy brothers eye, and perceiueſt not the beame that is in thine owne eye?</hi> But if the accuſation were neuer ſo iuſt and true, that there were ſome Miniſters (as God knoweth there bee too many) that confuted their
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16447:33"/>good Sermons with their lewde liues: yet that ought not to make altogether againſt all preaching, no more then the bad dealing of many Lawyers and Phyſicians doth vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly condemne the whole practice of Law and phyſicke. Beſides, there is in the Miniſtery, as in al other profeſſions, a number that are in truth no Miniſters, but euen the ſcum and refuſe of the Miniſtery; and therefore it is againſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and equitie, to turne their vile and diſſolute behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, to the generall diſgrace of al godly Miniſters. Againe, it is moſt true, that the beſt Miniſters that are, are not freed from the common infirmities and corruptions of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as the
<hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith of <hi>Elias,</hi> that though he were a man of excellent graces, yet
<hi>he was ſubiect to the ſame paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that we are.</hi> And as <hi>Paul and Barnabas</hi> confeſſed of themſelues,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 14.15.
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in the ſame word, when the men of <hi>Lyſtra</hi> would haue ſacrificed vnto them, <hi>O ye men,</hi> ſay they, <hi>why doe yee theſe things? we are euen men ſubiect to the like paſſions that ye be:</hi> neither are they indued with greater priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges againſt ſinne,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>7.</hi> tot.</note> then other men (as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> though rarely ſanctified, doth acknowledge of himſelfe.) And therefore,<note place="margin">Sen. de beata vita, lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> they are not able in all reſpects to performe and practiſe that which they teach to others: For if they could doe according to their doctrine, they were moſt happy.<note place="margin">Sen. epiſt.
<hi>94.</hi>
               </note> But alas, they that are moſt diligent and conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in admoniſhing others, cannot do it themſelues. And therfore, men ſhould rather labor to reape benefit by their preaching, then to wrangle and cauill at their liuing. For they are not to liue by the example of any man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.16.</note> but by the rules and precepts of the Word of God. And if the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> teach the way of God truly, as the
<hi>Phariſes</hi> ſaid of our Sauiour Chriſt, though himſelfe walke not alwaies <hi>with a right foote</hi> in the ſame;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.14.</note> the people are to follow his doctrine rather then his life. As our Sauiour Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that though the <hi>Scribes did ſay and not do:</hi> yet becauſe they <hi>ſate in Moſes his ſeat, they ſhould obſerue and doe whatſoeuer they bid them obſerue: Mat.</hi> 23.2, 3. For
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16447:33"/>doubtleſſe, as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith well to this purpoſe, He that teacheth wiſely and eloquently,<note place="margin">De doct. cir. li. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> and yet liueth wickedly, hee inſtructeth many men by his preaching, though he be vnprofitable to his owne ſoule. And a little after he addeth: They may be heard with profit to others, which doe vnprofitably themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diuiding the Word of truth aright.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Caictanus in locum. Beza, Piſcator, &amp;c. Leu. <hi>1.6, 7, 8, 12,</hi> &amp;c.</note>] The word here vſed is a borrowed ſpeech, taken, as ſome expound it, from <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters,</hi> that cut their timber by a right line: or as others interpret it, from that cutting and diuiding of the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which the Prieſts vſed in the Law: wherein the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſile</hi> expreſſeth the chiefe and principall office of a <hi>Miniſter.</hi> For ſeeing a Miniſter is implied in the moſt excellent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of al others, namely, in propounding and deliuering the Word of truth vnto Gods people, then which there is nothing greater nor more precious in all the world, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here inſtructeth him, how hee is rightly to handle the ſame. Now this right diuiding of the Word conſiſteth: firſt, in the right interpreting of the Scripture. Secondly, in the right diſpoſing of it in an apt and fit methode. Thirdly, in propounding and deliuering it in ſuch plaine words and eaſie ſtile, as the hearers may vnderſtand it. Fourthly, in applying the ſame vnto the hearers, as their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity is able to beare, and as their neceſſity doth require.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe, the Miniſter muſt be carefull to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret the place of Scripture, which he handleth, and to lay open the meaning of it, eſpecially if there bee any thing in it, that is hard to be vnderſtood. Thus did <hi>Ezra</hi> that learned <hi>Seribe, who was prompt in the Law of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra <hi>7.6.</hi>
               </note> , when he ſtood vp in the Pulpit which was made for the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Nebem. <hi>8.4, 8.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>he read in the booke of the Law of God distinctly, and gaue the ſenſe.</hi> Now the Scripture is beſt interpreted, when it is interpreted according to the meaning of the author of it, that is the Lord.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16.</note> And if any ſhall obiect,
<hi>who hath knowne the minde of the Lord?</hi> I anſwere, that if in interpreting the Scripture, we follow the analogie of faith, we cannot faile
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16447:34"/>of the mind of the Lord.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6.</note> As the
<hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith: <hi>If we prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> that is, if we expound the Scripture,
<hi>let vs propheſie accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the proportion of faith.</hi> Where he ſets downe the true
<hi>Canon</hi> of diſcerning a true interpretation from a falſe,<note place="margin">Beza in Rom.
<hi>12</hi>
               </note> namely, if it be examined according to the infallible max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes and principles of Chriſtian faith, contained in the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Creede,</hi> as it is commonly called, which from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the preaching of the Goſpell, was written as an <hi>epitome</hi> and abridgement therof, and was therfore worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called the rule and ſquare of faith. Whereunto agreeth that ſaying of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Doct. Chr. lib.
<hi>3.</hi>
               </note> When diligence applied, ſhall perceiue it vncertaine, how a thing muſt be diſtinguiſhed, or how it muſt be pronounced; let a man conſult with the rule of faith, which he hath receiued from plainer places of Scripture, and from the authoritie of the Church. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede for the moſt part we ſhall find, that the harder pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Scripture are interpreted by ſome other that are plainer.<note place="margin">Nehem. <hi>8.8.</hi> Exponendo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, dabant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligentiam per ſcripturam ipſam.</note> And therefore it is ſaid of
<hi>Ezra</hi> in the place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alleaged, as <hi>Tremelius</hi> readeth it, that when hee read the Law to the people, he opened the ſenſe, and gaue the vnderſtanding by the Scripture it ſelfe. But I will dwell no longer in the amplifying of this point: he that deſireth to reade more hereof, let him peruſe the learned Treatiſe of that worthy and reuerend man, Maſter Doctor <hi>Whittakers,</hi> wherein hee diſputeth the ſame at large againſt
<hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vſe of it, in a word, is to reprooue firſt all thoſe, who being ſworne vaſſals to the Pope, make him the onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter of the Scriptures. For howſoeuer they talke of the Fathers, and of generall Councels to bee conſulted withall in this caſe, yet in the ende they bring all to the Pope, and make him the vmpire in the whole buſineſſe. But the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> hath taught vs,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.</note> that <hi>as no man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the things of man, but the ſpirit of man that is within him: euen ſo no man knoweth the things of God, but the Spirit of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</note> That ſame Spirit, by <hi>whoſe inſpiration the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16447:34"/>whole Scripture was giuen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21.</note> and by whom <hi>the holy men</hi> that penned the Scripture <hi>were mooued,</hi> he muſt needes bee the beſt Interpreter of the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it reprooueth thoſe, who when they come to handle the Scripture in the hearing of Gods people, doe dwell onely in the rind or outward barke, and leaue the marrow and inward life and ſoule of the Scripture vntou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. For euen as the fruit of light metals,<note place="margin">Seneca. epiſt. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> is aboue in the top of the earth: but thoſe are richeſt, whoſe veine is hidden deepe, and will euery day more fully ſatiſſie him that diggeth: ſo there are many excellent things hid, as it were in the bowels of the holy Scriptures, which with a ſuperficiall and ouerly kind of ſtudie, cannot be attained vnto. And therefore, if it bee the dutie of all that ſtudie the Scriptures,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 5.39.
<hi>Prou.</hi> 2.4.</note> to <hi>ſearch them diligently,</hi> as our <hi>Sauiour</hi> ſaith, yea, <hi>to ſeeke for the knowledge thereof as for ſiluer, and digge for it as for hid treaſure.</hi> Much more is it the Miniſters dutie, who muſt open and explaine the ſame vnto the people.<note place="margin">In cap. <hi>3</hi> ad Epheſ.</note> And the rather, becauſe, as Saint <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> ſaith, There is no word, no ſyllable, no tittle or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, no little pricke in the holy Scriptures, but it is full of knowledge.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it reprooueth yet another ſort, who ſearch too farre into the Scriptures, and not contenting themſelues with the naturall fenſe and meaning of the place, draw all to
<hi>Allegories,</hi> and myſticall expoſitions. Concerning whom I will onely ſet downe what Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith in this caſe.<note place="margin">De Ciu. Dei. lib. <hi>17.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> As, ſaith he, they ſeeme to be much deceiued, which thinke there is nothing at all in the Scriptures, that ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any thing elſe, but that it was done after that manner: ſo they ſeeme to bee very bold, which auouch, that all things there, are wrapped vp and infolded in <hi>Allegories.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing wherein the right diuiding of the Word conſiſteth, is the right diſpoſing of the things to be deliuered in an apt and fit method. This is moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. For hereby euery thing commeth to haue his due place,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16447:35"/>that it may bee orderly and methodically vttered. It is a true ſaying that
<hi>Seneca</hi> hath to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>89.</hi>
               </note> It is a profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing, and very neceſſarie for him that would attaine to wiſedome, to haue
<hi>Philoſophy</hi> diuided, and that great body to bee diſpoſed into his members. For we are more eaſily brought by the parts vnto the knowledge of the whole. And a little after: Whatſoeuer is growne ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what great, it is more eaſily diſcerned, if it be ſeparated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to parts.<note place="margin">Macrob. Satur. lib. <hi>1.</hi> praefat.</note> It were to ſmall purpoſe, if a workeman had ſtones and timber, and all other ſtuffe neceſſarie for the building of an houſe, vnleſſe hee did diſpoſe and ſet euerie thing in order. So likewiſe, it is to as little purpoſe, for a Miniſter to be furniſhed with plentiful matter of inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for his hearers, vnleſſe hee obſerue an orderly methode in his teaching. Confuſion hath euer been accounted the mother of errour. And therefore in all things, men are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to proceede in an orderly courſe. In an armie, al things are placed in due order. And in a feaſt, the Sewer doth not onely ſet good meat on the table, but alſo diſpoſeth euery thing fitly in due place and time: much more ſhould this be obſerued of a Miniſter of the Word, in the right diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the food of mens ſoules.</p>
            <p>This ſerueth for the reproofe of thoſe that offend againſt this courſe in the two extremes. As firſt, ſuch as obſerue no order nor methode at all in handling of the word, but vtter whatſoeuer commeth on the tongues end. Whereby it commeth to paſſe, that many times they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from their Text they know not whither, and are as farre from the ſcope and ſenſe of it, as the Eaſt is from the Weſt. And hence alſo ariſeth another inconuenience, that they weary and tyre out their hearers by falling into odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and irkeſome tautologies and repetitions, wherein they often loſe themſelues in ſuch ſort, as they cannot get out.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>9.</hi> declam. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Whereas <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith wittily in diſgrace of ſuch a one, That it is no leſſe vertue to know when to make an end, then how to ſpeake.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:16447:35"/>
            <p>Secondly, ſuch as are ouer-curious in their diuiſions. A thing which <hi>Seneca</hi> condemneth in the handling of <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">In partes, non in fruſta diuidam. Ep. <hi>89.</hi> Jbid. Idem. n. vitij ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, nimia quod nulla diuiſio. Ibid.</note> I will diuide it, ſaith he, into parts, not into gob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets: and, It is profitable to haue it diuided, not minſed. And againe, The parts ſhould not bee innumerable and ouer-little. For it is as great a fault to haue too many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions, as none at all. And in a word, it is like to confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whatſoeuer is cut as ſmall as duſt. Much more is this a thing to be condemned, in diuiding of the holy Word of God. For they that are ſo nice in their diuiſions and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuiſions without end, are euen like the horſe, that when hee goeth to drinke, blundreth and troubleth the water with his foote, which was cleare before: ſo do theſe leaue the Word of God by this meanes more obſcure to the poore people, then they found it. Let it be our care there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to obſerue a plaine and eaſie methode, contenting our ſelues with the naturall diuiſion of the Text, that our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in their vnderſtanding, may be able to follow vs from point to point, as they are deliuered.</p>
            <p>The third thing wherein the right diuiding of the Word conſiſteth, is to propound and deliuer the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it, in ſuch apt and fit words, as the hearers may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it. Thus did <hi>Ezra</hi> open the law to the people in ſuch plaine manner, as he <hi>cauſed them to vnderſtand it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nehem. <hi>8.3.</hi>
               </note> And the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> profeſſeth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4.</note> that <hi>his preaching ſtood not in the intiſing ſpeech of mans wiſedome, but in plaine euidence of the Spirit, and of power.</hi> Hee did not ſet a gloſſe vpon the Word by humane art, as Marchants doe vpon their wares to make them more beautifull: but as he ſaith in the ſame Chapter,<note place="margin">Verſe <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He did ſpeake in words, which the holy Ghoſt taught him, comparing ſpirituall things with ſpirituall things.</hi> And indeed as the Goſpell proceedeth not from men, but from God: ſo it teacheth things that are aboue mans ſenſe and reaſon. And therefore in deliuering of the ſame, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhould vſe not humane, but diuine eloquence. Gods Word is ſpirituall; and therefore the ſpeech wherein it
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:16447:36"/>muſt be deliuered, muſt alſo be ſpirituall, euen taught by the Spirit. And that is a plaine and an eaſie ſtile, which is both moſt fit to carry the Word to the conſcience of euery man, and alſo to expreſſe the Maieſtie of the Word. And therefore the
<hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith in another place, that <hi>he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeake fine words in the Church with his vnderſtanding, that he might alſo inſtruct others, then ten thouſand wordes in a ſtrange tongue:</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Doct. Chr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi>
14.19. To which purpoſe Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> hath a good ſaying: Hee that teacheth, muſt not care with how great eloquence he teacheth: but with how great euidence and plaineneſſe.<note place="margin">Cicera in M. Anton. Philip. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> For what doth pureneſſe of ſpeech profit, which the vnderſtanding of the hearer doth not follow? Seeing there is no cauſe at all of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, if they doe not vnderſtand what wee ſpeake, for whoſe ſake wee ſpeake, that they may vnderſtand. And therefore he that teacheth, muſt ſhun all words that teach not.</p>
            <p>This ſerueth to reprooue all thoſe,<note place="margin">Horat. de art. poet.</note> that thinke ſcorne to condeſcend and ſtoope to the capacities of the poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but vſe vaine eloquence, ſuch as the hearers cannot vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand. As there are many that come into the Pulpit with an affected kinde of grauitie, as though they were great men, and with bombaſted and ſtrange new coined words labour to aſtoniſh and amaze their hearers, when (God knoweth) the matter is ſo idle and vaine, as that men of iudgement are almoſt ſicke to heare it. To ſuch the common prouerbe may be applied, There is great boaſt, and little roſt.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> Theſe men haue little deſire to edifie their hearers, or to conuert ſoules to God, when they will not ſpeake to their vnderſtanding. It hath euer been accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the beſt eloquence, and the beſt Orators haue alwaies made it their chiefeſt care, to expreſſe their meaning in the fitteſt and apteſt words that could be. And therfore,
<hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius</hi> the Emperour,<note place="margin">Sueton. in Octa.</note> a man of excellent ſpeech himſelfe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buketh <hi>M. Antonius</hi> as a mad man, as writing ſuch things which men might rather wonder at, then vnderſtand.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16447:36"/>Much more is this a fault in a Miniſter of the Word,<note place="margin">Seneca. epiſt. <hi>100</hi>
               </note> whoſe greateſt defire and endeuour ſhould bee to compoſe and order mans manners, and not their words, and to ſpeake to the hearts, and not to the eares of his hearers. Affected eloquence may for a time tickle and delight the eare, but it vaniſhethaway like the emptie ſound of muſicke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fruite.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt thing, wherein the right diuiding of the Word conſiſteth, is to apply the ſame to the capacitie and ſeuerall neceſſities of the hearers:<note place="margin">Caluin. in locum.</note> as if a Father ſhould cut a loafe of bread in pieces to feede his children. The doctrine muſt be tempered to the eſtate and condition of the auditorie. This is the chiefe of all the reſt, and therfore all the Interpreters beat moſt vpon it, as it were with one conſent. <hi>Beza</hi> ſaith: Let him conſider diligently, what the capacitie of his hearers is able to beare, and what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to edification. And <hi>Piſcator:</hi> Let him wiſely diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute it, and apply it to the neceſſities of his hearers. And
<hi>Aretius:</hi> Let it it bee referred to the capacitie of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers: for it is right when we propound to our hearers, that which they are able to conceiue, that which their faith can vnderſtand and beare. As a good Steward appointeth not ſo much food for an infant, as for thoſe that are at full age: nor for a ſicke, as for a ſtrong ſtomacke. And
<hi>Anſelmus:</hi> That thou mayeſt neither giue holy things to dogs, nor caſt pearles before ſwine: but mayeſt declare the Word, as it ought to bee, according to the qualitie of euery mans perſon, &amp;c. And <hi>Gorran;</hi> namely, By teaching and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to the neceſſitie of the hearers, that thou mayeſt giue ſtrong meate to them that are perfect, and to babes in Chriſt milke to drinke. And <hi>Lira:</hi> To propound words agreeable to euery one, namely, more high points for them that are wiſe, and more plaine and eaſie leſſons for the ſimple. And the ordinarie Gloſſe: According as is conuenient for euery one, that he may diſtribute ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things to them that are profound, and milke to little
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16447:37"/>children. And indeede, this is the chiefe part of a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> dutie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.42.</note> euen like <hi>a faithfull and a wiſe Steward to giue to euery one in the houſe their portion of meate in due ſeaſon:</hi> namely, that that is fit for them, and appertaineth vnto them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.13, 14.</note> And the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> compareth the grounds and principles of Religion, and points of
<hi>Catechiſone</hi> to <hi>milke,</hi> where with they that are <hi>babes in Chriſt</hi> muſt be fed: and the higher and profounder points of doctrine vnto <hi>ſtrong meate,</hi> which belongeth <hi>to them that are of age, &amp;c.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto his practice alſo was anſwerable: For he ſaith <hi>he gaue the Corinthians milke to drinke and not meate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe they were not able to beare it.</hi> One and the ſame exhortation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth not to all men. Oftentimes thoſe things hurt ſome, that profit other ſome. Bread which ſtrengtheneth the life of ſtrong men,<note place="margin">Greg. in prolog. part. <hi>3.</hi> paſt.</note> killeth little children. Hearbs which nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſome kind of creatures, kill other ſome, and a light whiſtling which appeaſeth Horſes, prouoketh Dogs. And therfore the ſpeech of the Teachers, muſt be framed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the qualitie of the hearers. Spirituall doctrine ſhould be deliuered after the manner of food, wherein ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rules of <hi>Phiſicke,</hi> foure things are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. Firſt, the ſubſtance of it, that it be wholeſome and fit to nouriſh, not poyſonſull and infectious: ſo the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that is taught, for ſubſtance muſt bee ſound and true, not falſe and hereticall. Secondly, the qualitie of it, that it be temperate and not too curious: ſo the manner of deliuering the Word muſt be plaine and eaſie, as hath bin ſaid alreadie. Thirdly, the quantity of it, that it be not too little, for that weakeneth nature, nor too much, for that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth and ouerwhelmeth. So the Miniſter, though hee neede not feare the exceſſe, becauſe hee is commanded <hi>to preach in ſeaſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi>
4.2.</note> 
               <hi>and out of ſeaſon:</hi> yet he muſt be carefull that he ſcant not the people of the Word, and ſo bring that <hi>famine</hi> among them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi>
8.11.</note> which the Lord threatneth. And laſt of all, the neceſſitie of him that eateth: For one kinde of foode is fit for a ſound body, and another for a ſicke:
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:16447:37"/>one for a young man, another for an old man: one for a weake man, another for a ſtrong man. There bee many things which are wholeſome to him that is in health, which are deadly to him that is ſicke. Honey is nouriſhing to old perſons, which yet, they ſay, hurteth children, and breedeth gripings in the belly which gnaw the bowels. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, there muſt be varietie of food, according to the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the diſeaſe. As one kinde of medicine is not vſed for all diſeaſes: ſo neither one doctrine agreeth to al men. To diuers diſeaſes,<note place="margin">Jn Apolog. ad Gul. Abbat.</note> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> there agree diuers medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, and ſtronger to them that are ſtronger. And a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine that abateth one diſeaſe, increaſeth the ſtrength of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Euery thing therefore muſt be fitted to the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the hearers. The Husbandman conſidereth well the qualitie of the ground,<note place="margin">Virgil. Georg. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> before he ſow his ſeede. For there is no ground that is fit for all ſeede. But ſome ſeede will grow better on one ſoile then on another. And ſome plants will thriue and proſper well in one kind of ground,<note place="margin">Ouid. de art. amandi.</note> which will not like at all in another. So the
<hi>Miniſter,</hi> that is, Gods Seeds-man, muſt conſider the qualitie of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, that he may fit his doctrine accordingly. The Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doth not alwaies vſe one kinde of net. Hee doth not fiſh with a caſting-net in the middeſt of the Sea, where the great fiſhes might breake his net; neither doth hee ſpread great nets in the ſhore, to take little fiſhes, which might preſently get out againe through the wide holes; for ſo hee ſhould loſe all his labour, but he fit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth his nets accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fiſh which he deſireth to catch: ſo the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> who is appointed <hi>to fiſh men to life,</hi> muſt apply his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in ſuch ſort, as hee ſeeth his hearers may be ſooneſt caught.<note place="margin">Cur. paſt. part. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> And therefore very well ſaith <hi>Gregorie</hi> to this purpoſe, that it is a matter of great ſtudie and labour, that in exhorting euery man, the Miniſter obſerue and regard euery thing, and that al things be diſpenſed to euery man, that doe properly appertaine vnto him. But much more labourſome is it, at one and the ſame time, with the voice
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16447:38"/>of one common exhortation to admoniſh innumerable hearers, labouring of diuers paſſions, that as it were with a two-edged ſword, he may cut off on both ſides the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of carnall thoughts, and like wraſtlers, may turne himſelfe cuery way in ſtriking.</p>
            <p>There are foure ſorts of Miniſters that come to be tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and reprooued by this doctrine: Firſt, ſuch as ſpend the time in deliuering vnprofitable &amp; impertinent things, ſuch as tend not at all to edification. As many take a great pride and buſie themſelues in anſwering friuolous and idle queſtions, which themſelues had made before, for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation of their wit.<note place="margin">A. Gellius. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> A man may ſay to them when they come downe, as <hi>Phauorinus</hi> the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſaid once to a boaſting
<hi>Grammarian,</hi> that had wearied him and others with an idle diſcourſe: They haue taught many things which they knew not before, and which they had no deſire to know.<note place="margin">Sen. epiſt. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> Or as <hi>Muſonius</hi> ſaid to ſuch another; Both the ſpeaker and the hearers loſe their labour.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuch as delight onely to handle obſcure and difficult points of doctrine, ſuch as few or none of their hearers are able to vnderſtand. A thing which euen the Heathen men haue condemned. Among the wiſe and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Grecians,</hi> the difficult and hard points of their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were neuer laid open to the diſcuſſing of ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but were cloſed vp with ſilence. And <hi>Varro</hi> remooued thoſe bookes which hee wrote of the profoundeſt queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and darkeſt myſteries of <hi>Theologie,</hi> from the ſight and knowledge of the multitude, and ſhut them vp within the wall of the Schooles. Much more ſhould the Miniſters of the Word bee carefull not to handle deepe and intricate points of Diuinitie in the hearing of poore ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.</note> leſt being
<hi>vnlearned,</hi> and not able to vnderſtand the ſame, they <hi>peruert them to their owne deſtruction,</hi> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſuch as deliuer good and profitable doctrine, but neuer apply it to mens conſciences. Doctrine and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16447:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhould not be ſeparated: yea,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi>
14.3.</note> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> maketh this the chiefe end of <hi>propheſying,</hi> that is, of preaching the Word, namely, <hi>to ſpeake to edifying, to exhortation, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</hi> And he exhorteth TIMOTHEVS, <hi>to giue attendance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi>
4.13.</note> as well <hi>to exhortation,</hi> as <hi>to doctrine.</hi> And in his preaching <hi>to rebuke and exhort,</hi> as well as <hi>to teach.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi>
4.2.</note> And the ſame he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo commandeth <hi>Titus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tis.</hi>
2.15.</note> And this himſelfe practiſed in all his Epiſtles, where firſt hee ſetteth downe matter of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, for the information of the iudgement, and then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth to matter of exhortation, for the reformation of manners. Doctrine indeed is profitable to perſwade the iudgement: but it is the application of the doctrine, that muſt worke vpon the heart and affections to winne them. So that application is the very life and edge of doctrine; without which it is dull, cold, barren, and as good as dead, and doth little good vnto the hearers. Not becauſe there is any defect in the Word, for it is perfect to all vſes and purpoſes: but becauſe few or none will apply the doctrine to themſelues, if the Miniſter neglect to doe it. For accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the common ſaying. That which is ſpoken to all, is ſpoken to none; becauſe euery man poſteth it off to his fellow, and will not take it to himſelfe, vnleſſe the Miniſter lay it home to his conſcience, and ſo apply it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi>
21.45.</note> (as Chriſt did to the chiefe <hi>Prieſts and Phariſes</hi>) as they may
<hi>perceiue that he ſpeaketh of them.</hi> If a <hi>Phiſician</hi> ſhould preſcribe neuer ſo excellent and approoued a medicine vnto his Patient, yet if it be not applied, it can doe him no good. No more can the doctrines of the Word, though neuer ſo excellent, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they be applied to the conſcience.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</note> The Word of God is a <hi>ſword,</hi> yea, <hi>a two-edged ſword</hi> to cut both waies. But it is like a ſword in a ſcabberd, and cannot cut at al, vnleſſe it be drawne out by application. Now the bare reading of the Word cannot doe this; it is the powerfull preaching of it that worketh this effect. And therefore <hi>Stapleton,</hi> though a Papiſt, and therfore no great friend to preaching, yet he preferreth it infinitely before reading. Preaching,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:16447:39"/>ſaith he, planteth yong beginners, and watereth them that goe forward. And in another place: The voice of God ſoundeth moſt effectually in Sermons, not in books. And many times it commeth to paſſe,<note place="margin">Plin. Secund. lib. <hi>2.</hi> epist.
<hi>3.</hi>
               </note> that one and the ſame ſentence, which being read, made no impreſsion in the mind, being ſpoken and deliuered in a Sermon, doth migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſtirre vs vp: and that which, though we know it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in reading, was not obſerued; in preaching is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with admiration,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2.</note> and doth wonderfully pleaſe vs, which before we paſſed ouer without any taſte.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, ſuch as giue themſelues to flatter their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, handling the Word of God
<hi>deceitfully;</hi> or as it is in the Vulgar Tranſlation,<note place="margin">Dominica.
<hi>22.</hi> poſt Pcnte. oſt.</note> 
               <hi>adulterating</hi> the Word: which <hi>Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> wittily expoundeth in this manner: They doe adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Word of God, ſaith he, that doe not thereby ſeeke to beget children vnto God, but onely to benefit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in pleaſing mens humours: as adulterers ſeeke for no iſſue, but onely intend their owne pleaſure. Theſe are they that fit their words, not to mens diſeafes, but to their defires, and doe not play the Phiſicians, but the clawbacks and the Paraſites. But euery faithfull <hi>Miniſter</hi> muſt firſt terrifie mens minds with the threatnings of the <hi>law,</hi> and then, if need ſtand, raiſe them vp with the promiſes of the <hi>Goſpell.</hi> And they that after this manner
<hi>diuide the Word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,</hi> are ſure by Gods bleſsing to ſee ſome fruits of their labour in the Church. The <hi>Miniſter</hi> muſt remember, that he hath to deale as well with the wicked, as with the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and therefore hee muſt ſo temper his doctrine, as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one may haue occaſion giuen him to deſpaire, nor the other may take to himſelfe the promiſes of God, when they are not due vnto him. This peraduenture will bee troubleſome, and it may be will procure him hatred, as the <hi>Galatians</hi> counted the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> PAVL
<hi>their enemie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe he told them the truth.</hi> But a Miniſter muſt not ſatisfie mens deſires, but faithfully execute that which God hath giuen him in commandement. And as <hi>Phyſicians</hi> do many times
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16447:39"/>powre bitter potions into mens mouthes, whether they will or no; and as
<hi>Surgeons</hi> cut and ſeare mens wounds, though they ſtruggle neuer ſo, if there bee neceſsitie: ſo the <hi>Miniſter</hi> muſt not reſpect the daintie and tender eares of the people, but muſt conſtantly aime at the ende of his Miniſtery. It was ſpoken in the commendation of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt,</hi> euen by the mouth of his greateſt enemies, that
<hi>he taught the way of God truly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.16.</note> 
               <hi>and conſidered no mans perſon.</hi> He taught in truth; in his doctrine he ſpake nothing to winne the fauour of any man, he deliuered nothing but what the truth it ſelfe ſuggeſted vnto him. So muſt it bee with all the Miniſters of Chriſt; they muſt neither reſpect the diſpleaſure, nor the fauour of any man. <hi>Stapleton</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth very peremptorily: They are the miniſters of Satan, that either perſwade, or promiſe, or dare giue peace to a wicked man without repentance.</p>
            <p>Finally, this doctrine ſerueth to ſtirre vp euery one of vs to the faithfull and ſincere performance of this dutie. We muſt not onely rehearſe the Word of God by the way, but by diuiding it aright, we muſt fitly apply it to ſeuerall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, times and perſons. And whether we purpoſe to teach, or to exhort, or to rebuke, or to comfort, wee muſt not pleaſe mens eares with an emptie ſound of words, and with curious ſpeeches made for oſtentation: but wee muſt labour to pierce euen into the hearts of men, and to ſpeake to their ſoules and conſciences. And therefore, to ſhut vp all with that ſpeech of Saint
<hi>Chryſostome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. de ſacerdou.</note> A Paſtor ſtandeth neede of great wiſedome, and ſixe hundred eyes, that he may euery way rightly diſcerne the diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mens minds, that he may know when he is to deale mildly and gently, and when roughly and ſharpely.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
